<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-09T00:25:23-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stedman Halliday</title><subtitle>Stedman Halliday is a technical generalist based in San Francisco creating values-aligned products, brands, media, and experiences.</subtitle><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Feb 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Feb 2025" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hermann-hesse-on-not-reading">Hermann Hesse on <em>not</em> reading</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Stand just once at the stage where the stone by the road means as much to you as Goethe and Tolstoy, you will thereafter gain from Goethe, Tolstoy, and all poets infinitely more value, more sap and honey, more affirmation of life and of yourself than ever before.</em></p>

  <p><em>For the works of Goethe are not Goethe and the volumes of Dostoevsky are not Dostoevsky, they are only an attempt, a dubious and never successful attempt, to conjure up the many-voiced multitudinous world of which he was the central point.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Hermann Hesse, <em>On Reading Books</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="thomas-merton-on-the-yips">Thomas Merton on the yips</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>When an archer is shooting for nothing he has all his skill. If he shoots for a brass buckle he is already nervous. If he shoots for a prize of gold he goes blind or sees two targets—he is out of his mind. His skill has not changed, but the prize divides him. He cares, he thinks more of winning than of shooting—and the need to win drains him of power.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Thomas Merton, <em>The Way of Chuang Tzu</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="seneca-the-younger-on-true-friendship">Seneca the Younger on true friendship</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>One who seeks friendship for favorable occasions strips it of all its nobility.</em></p>

  <p><em>If you consider any man a friend whom you do not trust as you trust yourself, you are mightily mistaken and you do not sufficiently understand what true friendship means… When friendship is settled, you must trust; before friendship is formed, you must pass judgment. Those persons indeed put last first and confound their duties, who… judge a man after they have made him their friend, instead of making him their friend after they have judged him. Ponder for a long time whether you shall admit a given person to your friendship; but when you have decided to admit him, welcome him with all your heart and soul. Speak as boldly with him as with yourself… Regard him as loyal and you will make him loyal.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Seneca the Younger</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Feb+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Jan 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Jan 2025" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs"><![CDATA[<h3><em>Stone Woman Gives Birth To A Child At Night</em>—Mount Eerie</h3>
<p>I’ve spent much of autumn’s turn to winter coasting around California in a sedan. I’m surprised at how long it’s taken me to give the roads their fair due with amount of time I’ve lived in California while owning a car. When Mount Eerie’s been on, I’ve found myself stopping more frequently to contemplate whatever’s knocking at the threshold of my attention—a scenic vista or a mundane slice of time. Awareness has taken on a wide range of flavors from slow and viscous to bold, sweeping, and dynamic. It’s an appropriate soundtrack for being present nowhere in particular.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2xeAZhRIegjVgPyd6Hr4x7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Circles</em>—Thrice</h3>
<p>There’s something I truly appreciate about the way many gems from Thrice’s wide-ranging discography allow themselves <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1879417785857761549">to be found</a> and sat within time and again. <em>Beggars</em> is one of my favorite records and <em>Circles</em> is a highlight that’s equal parts somber and expansive, with a small measure of twinkling hope. The lyrics characterize humans as intrepid yet futile in our perennial quests to cast ourselves into the dark and build upon what we know despite our ultimate ignorance, blindness, and fallibility. I haven’t watched these guys play in over 10 years (since the last dates of their farewell tour pre-reunion); perhaps it’s time to indulge a little nostalgia.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3VppAi6bcWZo9y2Gc0VmPg?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hey Listen</em>—Drug Church</h3>
<p>Drug Church’s <em>Prude</em> was one of my favorite releases of 2024. It doesn’t break much new ground sonically, but the songs are well written despite their structural and lyrical simplicity. The tracklist is built with vignettes—often crushing ones—of life on the other side of cracks in modern life that many people would rather just pretend aren’t there (along with the people who’ve fallen through them). Hearing <em>Hey Listen</em> reminds me of an unlucky kid I used to get into trouble with when I was running low on luck myself. It makes me feel abruptly anxious and awfully guilty; sapped and resigned to abject cowardice, shame, and disappointment, yet ultimately grateful. It is indeed tough to find an upside, but there’s no hope for luck without the intent to search. Thanks to <a href="https://x.com/em32label/status/1885020104917954783">Carlos Jarquin</a> for listening to me yap about sad shit. <a href="https://forms.gle/Dt7X7wBvobb9cPdC7">Go tell him</a> about a song that means something to you.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1lwgbuHay1ujrTepc28fck?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hollywood</em>—Toro y Moi, Benjamin Gibbard</h3>
<p>The end of last year saw me falling back into old patterns of landing myself in some total bullshit in Hollywood. Changing—truly and permanently changing—is a tall order. I guess I’m working my way up to it, but it’s really nobody’s business to even try to help me with this stuff anymore. On an entirely separate note, instrumental production is resonating with me here as creative inspiration. I’m sitting on several years’ worth of 8-bar guitar loops that need arrangements to call a home and I had a fun time bringing some field recordings of indigenous chants and my gamelan percussion fiddlings over to a local session with <a href="https://soundcloud.com/hexani">hex_</a> earlier this month. <em>I need to finish things!</em></p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/5NsV5awvlAnMcz01zJWPnQ?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Heavyheart</em>—munro</h3>
<p>Leave it to genre-bending Internet music provacateur in chief <a href="https://x.com/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt</a> to run with <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1831481465290551337">the meme</a> until it gets far enough out of hand to yield an exquisitely curated <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/78fb8mCjI4ZFk50yeiqYNM?si=s0o_XCk5QqCa01sgWprj8Q">27-song compilation release</a> from Tabula Rasa with a <a href="https://www.tabularasarecords.net/collections/hit-em">complementary merch drop.</a> munro’s track was the stickiest in my rotation, but the gamut covered by the other contributors showcases some really exciting production. 212 BPM. 5/4 time. Super crunched out sounds. Thank you to Drew for the tweet that started it all, and of course Thank You Dream Girl.</p>
<div class="mt-100 flex-center"><div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">had a dream I was at a rave talking to a girl and she told me about a genre called “hit em” that is in 5/4 time at 212 bpm with super crunched out sounds thank you dream girl</p>&mdash; DREW DANIEL (@DDDrewDaniel) <a href="https://twitter.com/DDDrewDaniel/status/1817910903557570569?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 29, 2024</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

</div></div>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7e7nlauAQ7866PPFMuxtgx?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>HEAL</em>—Machinedrum, AKTHESAVIOR, Deniro Farrar</h3>
<p>Machinedrum’s curatorial efforts on the compilation mentioned above came fresh off the heels of a deluxe LP release. <em>3FOR82_D3LUX3</em> brings even more solid cuts to the table than the original release from back in the spring and this track found me again at the right time in life to embed itself deeply in my rotation. It’s been over 10 years since the <em>Vapor City</em> era and somehow this guy is still finding new things to execute very well. I enjoy the range of experimentation in his crossovers into black music. Not everything hits for me—e.g. I don’t <em>dislike</em> the Jesse Boykins III collaborations, but it’s easy to find R&amp;B I’m more fond of. <em>Kane Train</em> with Freddy Gibbs (2020) was a smash by comparison; a definitive step up in Machinedrum’s ability to find a pocket in hip-hop production with vocal features. <em>HEAL</em> (2024) takes that deeper than production and performance into the realm of transcendent emotional appeal. It’s perhaps a tad less instrumentally inventive but still exquisitely arranged, sitting behind the vocal where it needs to yet still placing melodic variation and dynamic highs where they fit best. Stellar and moving vocal performance and message: life is hard… find a way to push through.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Vz1AtKebBGUyQm6O77Yan?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Lullaby</em>—TURQUOISEDEATH</h3>
<p>I’ve been riding around at night a lot with TURQUOISEDEATH. I’d comfortably put <em>Kaleidoscope</em> in the 2024 sleepers category; definitely unexpected replay value. Solid balance of ethereal ambiance, danceable tempos, and pedal to the metal breakbeat-filled DnB/jungle-esque goodness—not terribly novel, but thoroughly enjoyable.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1NKyiSyZyvz6mHgB4KSKbb?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>
<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Jan+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /><published>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" alt="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /></p>

<p class="mt-200">Ever wished you could hack your sleep schedule, beat jetlag, or stay sharp through an all-nighter without feeling like a zombie? Enter propranolol—a seemingly ordinary beta blocker with some extraordinary tricks up its sleeve. From calming anxiety to resetting your internal clock, propranolol might just be the secret weapon you've been looking for to take control of your sleep and energy levels.</p>

<div class="mv-200 divider-thin"></div>

<h2 id="overview-of-beta-blockers">Overview of beta blockers</h2>

<h3 id="mechanism-of-action">Mechanism of action</h3>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<h3 id="beta-blocker-subtypes">Beta blocker subtypes</h3>

<p>Cardioselective beta blockers mainly work on the heart by blocking beta-1 receptors, which helps lower heart rate and blood pressure. Because they focus more on the heart, they don’t affect the lungs as much, making them safer for people with breathing problems like asthma or COPD.</p>

<p>Non-selective beta blockers block both beta-1 and beta-2 receptors. Since beta-2 receptors are found in the lungs, blood vessels, and muscles, these drugs can affect more than just the heart. This can cause side effects like tightening of the airways, making them less safe for people with asthma or COPD.</p>

<h3 id="applications-for-anxiety">Applications for Anxiety</h3>

<p>This mechanism is particularly beneficial for individuals with social anxiety or general anxiety disorders, as it mitigates physical symptoms of anxiety.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="propranolol-specifics">Propranolol specifics</h2>

<p>Propranolol is a non-selective beta blocker. It is the most lipophilic (fat-soluble) among them, which enables it to cross the blood-brain barrier more effectively.</p>

<h3 id="effects-on-circadian-rhythm">Effects on circadian rhythm</h3>

<p>When propranolol crosses into the brain, it affects the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) in a way that mimics morning blue light exposure. This can lower the body’s natural production of melatonin, which might lead to insomnia and nightmares.</p>

<h3 id="application">Application</h3>

<p>Propranolol can be used to intentionally reduce melatonin production, making it easier to stay awake longer, such as when pulling an all-nighter. It can also be used to reset a chronically desynchronized sleep schedule or overcome jetlag.</p>

<h2 id="example-reversing-a-nocturnal-routine">Example: reversing a nocturnal routine</h2>

<h3 id="background">Background</h3>

<p>Drue Wetsel, a 25-year-old software engineer, has been stuck in a nocturnal routine, habitually falling asleep at 5 am and waking up around 1 pm. He wants to reset his sleep schedule to fall asleep at midnight and wake up at 8 am to align better with a more typical workday and improve his overall health.</p>

<h3 id="circadian-reset-protocol">Circadian reset protocol</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>5 am:</strong> Drue goes to bed at his usual time and sets an alarm for 8 am, planning to get only 3 hours of sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>8 am:</strong> He wakes up, takes propranolol, and uses caffeine to power through the day on minimal sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 pm – 6 pm:</strong> Drue keeps himself busy and alert, using a brief NSDR (non-sleep deep rest) session to avoid napping and maintain energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 am:</strong> Exhausted, Drue finally goes to bed at his new target bedtime, setting an alarm for 8 am to reinforce the new schedule.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Following days:</strong> Drue sticks to the midnight-to-8 am sleep schedule, using propranolol and mild stimulants as needed, until it becomes his new norm.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="additional-medical-applications">Additional medical applications</h2>

<p><strong>Thyroid storm management:</strong> Propranolol helps manage dangerously fast heart rate and high blood pressure caused by excessive thyroid hormone by slowing down the heart and easing other symptoms like anxiety and tremors.</p>

<p><strong>Prevention of cardiac remodeling:</strong> propranolol can help prevent changes in heart structure caused by heart failure (however, other beta blockers are more commonly used for this purpose).</p>

<p><strong>Prophylactic use in cirrhotics:</strong> variceal bleeding occurs when swollen veins in the esophagus or stomach burst and bleed due to liver disease. Non-selective beta blockers like propranolol help prevent this by reducing pressure in those veins.</p>

<p><strong>Treatment of essential tremors:</strong> essential tremors cause uncontrollable shaking, often in the hands. Propranolol helps reduce this shaking, making it easier for people to do everyday tasks.</p>

<h2 id="cautions-and-side-effects">Cautions and side effects</h2>

<p><strong>Respiratory concerns:</strong> propranolol and other non-selective beta blockers can exacerbate asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In conclusion, propranolol is a versatile non-selective beta blocker with a range of applications, from managing anxiety and essential tremors to preventing serious complications in conditions like thyroid storm and cirrhosis. Its ability to cross the blood-brain barrier makes it particularly effective for altering circadian rhythms, offering a solution for those needing to reset their sleep schedules. However, caution is necessary, especially for individuals with respiratory conditions, as propranolol can exacerbate issues like asthma and COPD. Consult a healthcare professional for guidance before using propranolol.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p><a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Circadian+Rhythm+Alteration+with+Propranolol.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you enjoyed this post or if you’ve got any corrections I should know about. Special thanks to <a href="https://substack.com/@quixoteknight">quixoteknight</a> for enriching this post with invaluable insights into medical pharmacology. Read what they have to say about melatonin next.</p>

<h2 class="mt-200 text-center">Related content</h2>
<div class="substack-post-embed" style="margin: 0 auto; border-radius: 12px; overflow: hidden"><p lang="en">Melatonin: MMTYWTK Addendum by QK</p><p>Fun Practical Applications of Abusing Endogenous Neurohormones</p><a data-post-link="" href="https://optimizeeverything.substack.com/p/melatonin-mmtywtk-addendum">Read on Substack</a></div>
<script async="" src="https://substack.com/embedjs/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday and [quixoteknight](https://substack.com/@quixoteknight)</name></author><category term="health" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="sleep" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reset your sleep clock or beat jetlag with beta blockers]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Q&amp;amp;A: Why are toxic, competitive attitudes so common in the design community?</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Q&amp;amp;A: Why are toxic, competitive attitudes so common in the design community?" /><published>2017-11-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-massimo.webp" alt="Massimo Vignelli" /></p>

<p class="mt-200"><em>Q&amp;A is a column in which I'll post long-form answers to thought-provoking questions. This particular question and its answer are reposted from thread in <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/340004709510141">Designers Guild</a>, a Facebook community that I moderate. Designers Guild consists of 10,000+ designers committed to discussing, learning, and growing together.</em></p>

<h2 class="mt-200">The question</h2>

<p><em>A number of discussions last week revolved around design’s prevailing cultural prioritization of competition over cooperation (the collaborative ethos we often see in software development and engineering circles, especially in open-source communities).</em></p>

<p>Some quotes for context:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>There’s a heavy tendency for designers to compete and contrast themselves with one another rather than cooperate…</em></p>

  <p><em>I guess what I’m not understanding is why designers are less primed to being good at working together in an open-source context than engineers…</em></p>

  <p><em>I’ve also seen design folks click [sic] out into camps, and compete with each other when there was no reason to… (yikes, why do we do that, it’s like we need the pat on the back or the recognition…)</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It would seem that toxic, competitive attitudes which impede collaboration are a widely recognizable problem in the design industry. But the question is: <em>where does the mindset behind the toxicity come from?</em></p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="the-answer">The answer</h2>

<p>One easy answer that addresses the cultural difference between design and software engineering in this regard is rooted in software’s historical context.</p>

<h3 id="a-brief-history-of-collaboration-in-software-development">A brief history of collaboration in software development</h3>

<p><strong>Software has grown into the monolith it is today with transparency, openness, and community hardwired into its DNA.</strong></p>

<p>Because software development originated in academic research environments, the principles of cooperation and openness for the sake of collective intellectual advancement were easy carryovers from the scientific and academic communities. It also helped that software was not the massively commoditized industry that it has since become; originally there was little incentive to stray from this model.</p>

<p>Richard Stallman effectively spearheaded the free software movement when he announced the GNU Project. In 1985, he founded the <a href="https://fsf.org">Free Software Foundation</a> and penned the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/gnu/manifesto.html">GNU Manifesto</a>, enumerating his reasons for believing so strongly in the values that free software promulgates. Some standout excerpts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I consider that the Golden Rule requires that if I like a program I must share it with other people who like it. Software sellers want to divide the users and conquer them, making each user agree not to share with others. I refuse to break solidarity with other users in this way. I cannot in good conscience sign a nondisclosure agreement or a software license agreement…</em></p>

  <p><em>So that I can continue to use computers without dishonor, I have decided to put together a sufficient body of free software so that I will be able to get along without any software that is not free…</em></p>

  <p><em>Everyone will be permitted to modify and redistribute GNU, but no distributor will be allowed to restrict its further redistribution. That is to say, proprietary modifications will not be allowed. I want to make sure that all versions of GNU remain free…</em></p>

  <p><em>Once GNU is written, everyone will be able to obtain good system software free, just like air…</em></p>

  <p><em>Copying all or parts of a program is as natural to a programmer as breathing, and as productive. It ought to be as free.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Richard Stallman, <em>GNU Manifesto</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bigquote">In a word, what Stallman values so staunchly (in addition to freedom) can be described as <em>fellowship.</em></blockquote>

<p>Linus Torvalds followed in Stallman’s footsteps with the open release of the Linux kernel’s source in the early 1990s (later relicensed under a GNU General Public License: a free software license authored by Stallman himself). The combination of GNU’s free software and operating system with the Linux kernel brought about the first entirely free software environment for users. Neither that achievement, nor the entirety of the modern-day Linux ecosystem (not to mention countless other technologies) would be possible without the spirit of fellowship that united thousands of volunteer developers with the aim of constructive collaboration.</p>

<p>The idea of fellowship propagated even further throughout the development community with the advent of the World Wide Web. Tim Berners-Lee proposed and executed his early vision of the Web at CERN, another research environment where open informational exchange was a value of paramount importance. Furthermore, the Web was created for exactly that purpose: it enabled researchers to exchange and browse information with far more efficiency… and exchange they did!</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Tim Berners-Lee" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-berners-lee.webp" />
    <figcaption>Tim Berners-Lee at CERN in 1994 next to an early iteration of the World Wide Web.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Collaboration and the willing exchange of information continue to be absolutely crucial to the world of software development today. It’s not difficult to see how these ethics are structurally enforced by some undeniable industry realities, specifically:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The idea that “everything is built on something that was built on something that was built in 1970” encourages borrowing code as a productive and necessary practice.</li>
  <li>Carefully reading documentation (authored by some other developer) and searching for sources of previously shared information (e.g. Google-fu and browsing Stack Overflow) are some of the most essential platform-independent skills for any professional developer out there today.</li>
</ul>

<p>So far, this historical background does an alright job of explaining how collaboration has been valuable to software development in the past, but we still lack a satisfactory answer to our main question.</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">I believe that the essential differences in each industry's culture surrounding willing collaboration come down to categorical differences in how creative value is construed.</blockquote>

<h3 id="why-is-fellowship-valuable-to-engineers">Why is fellowship valuable to engineers?</h3>

<p>As a discipline, engineering is outcome-oriented and largely favors vertical progression. Achievement usually means rigorously honing a focused skillset and digging deeper to spawn new technical outcomes within a specific scope or domain. As an analogy, consider two miners, each in search of a different mineral—let’s say iron and lead. The iron miner has no real interest in unearthing lead other than to trade it with the lead miner for the iron ore that they recover, and the lead miner has a similar attitude. They’ve staked different claims and stated different goals, so they’re not truly competing with one another. However, each stands to gain immensely from collaborating with the other.</p>

<p>By trading ore with one another and sharing mining secrets and techniques, the miners can increase both of their yields. It doesn’t even matter if the result is that the iron miner extracts more lead ore: they would’ve used the same amount of mining resources in their search for iron anyway, but now they can earn revenue by trading with their neighbor. Similarly for the lead miner, all the lead ore that they are trading with the iron miner to obtain would’ve been inaccessible to them anyway, seeing as the iron miner has already staked their claim on that land. This is now ore in the hand that can be traded for at face value rather than prospected for with expected losses.</p>

<p>In a similar fashion, developers don’t really see themselves as direct competitors with others who happen to be digging a different hole (they may often view each other as indirect competitors in the abstract, which leads to rampant impostor syndrome and software development’s own brand of toxic and condescending attitudes, but that’s another story).</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Coal miners" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-miners.webp" />
    <figcaption>"Real miners don't use Pascal." 🙄</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Additional value can also be created on massive scales when insights arise from the intersection of a developer’s own vertical progress with their understanding of parallel innovations. This is similar to the <a href="https://priceonomics.com/the-correlation-between-arts-and-crafts-and-a/">correlation between artistic hobbies and scientific achievement</a>. To summarize, Nobel-Prize-winning scientists are 280% as likely to have a hobby in the arts as are scientists in general. The underlying theory is that experience and vertical achievement in the sciences can cross-pollinate with avocational creative exploration to lend new insights to the scientist’s practical career endeavors.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Nobel scientist hobbies" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-nobel-hobbies.webp" />
    <figcaption>A University of Michigan study found that elite scientists have a particular affinity for artistic hobbies.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>A good example of value created by crossover innovation in software is how neural networks (a highly academic subject confined to the relatively inaccessible fields of machine learning and deep learning research only a few years ago) are now a fairly commonplace component of consumer technology products. This couldn’t have happened without parallel research in the fields that artificial intelligence is applied to, such as imaging (computer vision and image recognition) and language and acoustics (speech recognition and natural language processing). A neat example that demonstrates both of these ideas is the application of deep learning to <a href="https://blogs.nvidia.com/blog/2016/05/25/deep-learning-paints-videos/">visual art processing</a> and <a href="https://shafeentejani.github.io/2016-12-27/style-transfer/">style transfer</a> (the abilities of AI to identify the styles of a images and apply them to other images).</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Deep Photo Style Transfer" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-style-transfer.webp" />
    <figcaption>Researchers from Cornell University and Adobe take an original photo (left) and a reference image (center) as input and combine them output a new image (right). This technique is called <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.07511">Deep Photo Style Transfer</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It turns out that accepting help and being helpful in return are… well, helpful! In the famed words of Sir Isaac Newton (from a letter to Robert Hooke about collaboration, of all subjects):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>If I have seen further it is by standing on ye sholders [sic] of Giants.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Sir Isaac Newton, letter to Robert Hooke</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bigquote">It doesn't discredit developers to borrow the techniques that they use to achieve their goals because it is the rigor behind executing outcomes that is valued and celebrated.</blockquote>

<p>That’s not to say that the creativity and ingenuity involved in execution are not praiseworthy (in fact, they are frequently lauded). It’s just that the first and most important question in software development is whether or not the outcome actually works.</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">Ultimately, being a developer is all about having the grit to corral everything together into a practical outcome.</blockquote>

<h3 id="why-do-designers-systematically-fail-to-value-fellowship">Why do designers systematically fail to value fellowship?</h3>

<p>In contrast to software engineering’s cultural endorsement of vertical progression, creative disciplines (design included) largely incentivize horizontal progression. This is an inevitable consequence of rewarding the originality of outcomes and intellect over the rigor of process. For a long time, being a big-name designer hasn’t been about developing reliable and repeatable processes to consistently meet industrial goals. Instead, the idea of success in the design world has largely revolved around the ability to effectively wield cultural capital and trade on style, voice, and personality.</p>

<p>To return to the mining metaphor, imagine if the miners from before had redefined their success along the terms of who has claimed the best stake (not to be confused with the stake that has the highest mineral yield… just the “best” stake, whatever that may arbitrarily mean). The game then becomes all about seeking out new ground, staking a claim, and defining your hole according to criteria that position it as superior to all others dug before it. Within this value system and with these judgment criteria, every miner actually is in direct competition with the next. The design analogs:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Seeking out new ground</strong>—generating and executing on an “original” concept or aesthetic</li>
  <li><strong>Staking a claim</strong>—accepting credit for the intellectual labor involved in the generating novelty and/or success of a project</li>
  <li><strong>Touting your hole as superior</strong>—cleverly rationalizing your design decisions; criticizing others’ design decisions in equal or greater measure; utilizing past successes, cultural knowledge, voice, and cultural identity to increase your brand profile as a designer</li>
</ul>

<blockquote class="bigquote">In other words, an inordinate amount of the work concerns talking about the work in order to convince others of the the value of the design solution and, by extension, the designer's originality and intellect.</blockquote>

<p>I’ll let Mike M. tell it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Everyone who ever told you good work sells itself was a lying jerk… I was told that good work, really good work, sold itself. And that if you had to stoop to selling it you were demeaning the profession. This is shit advice from shit people.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Mike Monteiro</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Monteiro makes a <a href="https://medium.com/mule-design/everyone-who-ever-told-you-good-work-sells-itself-was-a-lying-jerk-65acc1a72f74">good case</a> for why it’s a necessity for designers to develop ancillary presentation skills and learn how to speak about their work. But if it’s true that really good work can’t even sell itself, surely there must be a problem, no? <strong>The implication here is that clients cannot readily understand the value of design without some kind of presentation.</strong></p>

<p>Why is the value of design so inapparent? I’d posit that it’s because most designers don’t explicitly understand how exactly design adds value to its substrates in accordance with their own values and thinking patterns. They may have an intuition for the fact that design has a net-positive effect when executed appropriately, but the fact that the cult of design so frequently values the wrong things (perceived aesthetic novelty and conceptual intellect) makes the value of design incredibly difficult for even designers to quantify.</p>

<p><strong>It would behoove many a designer to realize that value in the realm of commerce is a business concept and not a philosophical one.</strong> Convincing other people of design’s value is about quantifying what it can do for their businesses. Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RKXZ7t_RiOE">this video</a> posted in a Designers Guild discussion this week where Chris Do gives a phenomenal master class in just some of the ways that designers can discuss value when doing business. (Note: it’s very different from the ways in which most designers represent the value they can provide to businesses and that’s why it’s successful.)</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>The current difficulty with surmounting the design industry’s impasse of misplaced philosophical values arises from the fact that most of 20th century design ran on <strong>auteur theory</strong> (the idea that a single creator is responsible for executing all aspects of a collaborative creative work). Auteur theory is what emphasizes stylistic originality and the intellect of the individual creator above all other important factors that bring a creative project to fruition.</p>

<p>Auteur theory is why we have design “legends” and “rockstars.” It’s why <a href="https://eyeondesign.aiga.org/the-11-types-of-trendy-graphic-design-paul-rand-hated/">Paul Rand</a>, <a href="http://designobserver.com/article.php?id=15458">Massimo Vignelli</a>, and many other a graphic design granddad have wielded cultural capital amassed over their entire careers to convincingly decry nearly everything that’s succeeded them in the postmodern era. Although their criticisms are not entirely invalid, one might question the motives behind such vigorous disapproval of alternative approaches to craft.</p>

<p>How else could these legends of old defend their status as auteurs other than with vigorous criticism? They’re supposed to be singular geniuses who are irreplaceable provisioners of value. In practice, that all too often translates to devaluing things that deviate from modernism (the one <em>successful</em> and <em>correct</em> way to add value—if clients don’t believe that, modernists don’t get paid; if the culture doesn’t believe that, modernists don’t get legacy clout). This is the fault of auteur theory at its peak, and its vestiges are largely to blame for the commonplace toxicity and non-collaborative values in design today.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="David Chathas collage" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-david-chathas-collage.webp" />
    <figcaption>It's 2017, y'all still mad?! (Images courtesy of <a href="http://www.bestgraphicdesignerintheworld.com/">David Chathas</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Another problem with rewarding formal originality and perceived intellectual inventiveness over all else is that it makes it difficult to trace the genealogy of ideas, which tell us a lot about how to create value in the future. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oww7oB9rjgw">“Steal like an artist,”</a> has quite a different ring to it than Newton’s modest musings on the shoulders of giants. It’s not too often that software strictly requires anyone to provide citations either, but because the field has developed a culture that does not penalize collective achievement and the re-synthesis of existing ideas, the majority of developers share their resources quite enthusiastically.</p>

<p>In contrast, the value system in the present design landscape ensures that in most cases, we still systematically fail to attribute value to team members whose work goes unrecognized. Additionally, appreciating the output of the designers whose work an outcome intellectually builds upon is optional at best… but things seem to be getting better.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h3 id="a-better-future-for-the-value-of-design">A Better Future for the Value of Design</h3>

<p>One good thing about the intersections of design, technology, business, and analytics is that creatives are being held to a more universal and honest standard that is quantifiable from a business perspective. It’s good to be original to the extent that one can, but what do novel outcomes beget in the real world; in other peoples’ utilitarian value systems?</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">When we cease to reward design outcomes solely for perceived originality and individual intellect, and instead begin to hold them to standards defined by results, maybe the world will better understand the value of design.</blockquote>

<p><em>How suitable was this strategy for the target market? How did this campaign create growth?</em> <strong>If design is a practice of aesthetic utility, designers should probably ask utilitarian questions and take utilitarian measurements.</strong> The leaders who ushered in the precursors of modern design at the Bauhaus a century ago may have made strides into adopting a more scientific process for creating work… but as far as feedback for assessing work, we’re mostly still thinking like artists.</p>

<p>Perhaps if designers start measuring their outcomes in addition to critiquing them, everyone’s contributions to process can come forth and find value. <strong>When people feel valued for their contributions, they contribute abundantly instead of viewing intellect as a scarce resource to sequester for their own gain.</strong> When designers manage to value one another and incentivize valuable contribution on an industry-wide scale, the benefits of collaboration and fellowship will have become central community tenets.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>What did you think of this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Q%26A%3A+Why+are+toxic%2C+competitive+attitudes+so+common+in+the+design+community%3F.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know if you’ve got thoughts on any of these topics.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday for [Prototypr.io](https://blog.prototypr.io/)</name></author><category term="design" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="software" /><category term="community" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Structural and historical rationales for fellowship and competition in design practice]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>