<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-04T06:33:17-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stedman Halliday</title><subtitle>Stedman Halliday is a technical generalist based in San Francisco creating values-aligned products, brands, media, and experiences.</subtitle><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Feb 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Feb 2025" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hermann-hesse-on-not-reading">Hermann Hesse on <em>not</em> reading</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Stand just once at the stage where the stone by the road means as much to you as Goethe and Tolstoy, you will thereafter gain from Goethe, Tolstoy, and all poets infinitely more value, more sap and honey, more affirmation of life and of yourself than ever before.</em></p>

  <p><em>For the works of Goethe are not Goethe and the volumes of Dostoevsky are not Dostoevsky, they are only an attempt, a dubious and never successful attempt, to conjure up the many-voiced multitudinous world of which he was the central point.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Hermann Hesse, <em>On Reading Books</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="thomas-merton-on-the-yips">Thomas Merton on the yips</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>When an archer is shooting for nothing he has all his skill. If he shoots for a brass buckle he is already nervous. If he shoots for a prize of gold he goes blind or sees two targets—he is out of his mind. His skill has not changed, but the prize divides him. He cares, he thinks more of winning than of shooting—and the need to win drains him of power.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Thomas Merton, <em>The Way of Chuang Tzu</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="seneca-the-younger-on-true-friendship">Seneca the Younger on true friendship</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>One who seeks friendship for favorable occasions strips it of all its nobility.</em></p>

  <p><em>If you consider any man a friend whom you do not trust as you trust yourself, you are mightily mistaken and you do not sufficiently understand what true friendship means… When friendship is settled, you must trust; before friendship is formed, you must pass judgment. Those persons indeed put last first and confound their duties, who… judge a man after they have made him their friend, instead of making him their friend after they have judged him. Ponder for a long time whether you shall admit a given person to your friendship; but when you have decided to admit him, welcome him with all your heart and soul. Speak as boldly with him as with yourself… Regard him as loyal and you will make him loyal.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Seneca the Younger</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Feb+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Jan 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Jan 2025" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs"><![CDATA[<h3><em>Stone Woman Gives Birth To A Child At Night</em>—Mount Eerie</h3>
<p>I’ve spent much of autumn’s turn to winter coasting around California in a sedan. I’m surprised at how long it’s taken me to give the roads their fair due with amount of time I’ve lived in California while owning a car. When Mount Eerie’s been on, I’ve found myself stopping more frequently to contemplate whatever’s knocking at the threshold of my attention—a scenic vista or a mundane slice of time. Awareness has taken on a wide range of flavors from slow and viscous to bold, sweeping, and dynamic. It’s an appropriate soundtrack for being present nowhere in particular.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2xeAZhRIegjVgPyd6Hr4x7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Circles</em>—Thrice</h3>
<p>There’s something I truly appreciate about the way many gems from Thrice’s wide-ranging discography allow themselves <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1879417785857761549">to be found</a> and sat within time and again. <em>Beggars</em> is one of my favorite records and <em>Circles</em> is a highlight that’s equal parts somber and expansive, with a small measure of twinkling hope. The lyrics characterize humans as intrepid yet futile in our perennial quests to cast ourselves into the dark and build upon what we know despite our ultimate ignorance, blindness, and fallibility. I haven’t watched these guys play in over 10 years (since the last dates of their farewell tour pre-reunion); perhaps it’s time to indulge a little nostalgia.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3VppAi6bcWZo9y2Gc0VmPg?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hey Listen</em>—Drug Church</h3>
<p>Drug Church’s <em>Prude</em> was one of my favorite releases of 2024. It doesn’t break much new ground sonically, but the songs are well written despite their structural and lyrical simplicity. The tracklist is built with vignettes—often crushing ones—of life on the other side of cracks in modern life that many people would rather just pretend aren’t there (along with the people who’ve fallen through them). Hearing <em>Hey Listen</em> reminds me of an unlucky kid I used to get into trouble with when I was running low on luck myself. It makes me feel abruptly anxious and awfully guilty; sapped and resigned to abject cowardice, shame, and disappointment, yet ultimately grateful. It is indeed tough to find an upside, but there’s no hope for luck without the intent to search. Thanks to <a href="https://x.com/em32label/status/1885020104917954783">Carlos Jarquin</a> for listening to me yap about sad shit. <a href="https://forms.gle/Dt7X7wBvobb9cPdC7">Go tell him</a> about a song that means something to you.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1lwgbuHay1ujrTepc28fck?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hollywood</em>—Toro y Moi, Benjamin Gibbard</h3>
<p>The end of last year saw me falling back into old patterns of landing myself in some total bullshit in Hollywood. Changing—truly and permanently changing—is a tall order. I guess I’m working my way up to it, but it’s really nobody’s business to even try to help me with this stuff anymore. On an entirely separate note, instrumental production is resonating with me here as creative inspiration. I’m sitting on several years’ worth of 8-bar guitar loops that need arrangements to call a home and I had a fun time bringing some field recordings of indigenous chants and my gamelan percussion fiddlings over to a local session with <a href="https://soundcloud.com/hexani">hex_</a> earlier this month. <em>I need to finish things!</em></p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/5NsV5awvlAnMcz01zJWPnQ?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Heavyheart</em>—munro</h3>
<p>Leave it to genre-bending Internet music provacateur in chief <a href="https://x.com/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt</a> to run with <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1831481465290551337">the meme</a> until it gets far enough out of hand to yield an exquisitely curated <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/78fb8mCjI4ZFk50yeiqYNM?si=s0o_XCk5QqCa01sgWprj8Q">27-song compilation release</a> from Tabula Rasa with a <a href="https://www.tabularasarecords.net/collections/hit-em">complementary merch drop.</a> munro’s track was the stickiest in my rotation, but the gamut covered by the other contributors showcases some really exciting production. 212 BPM. 5/4 time. Super crunched out sounds. Thank you to Drew for the tweet that started it all, and of course Thank You Dream Girl.</p>
<div class="mt-100 flex-center"><div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">had a dream I was at a rave talking to a girl and she told me about a genre called “hit em” that is in 5/4 time at 212 bpm with super crunched out sounds thank you dream girl</p>&mdash; DREW DANIEL (@DDDrewDaniel) <a href="https://twitter.com/DDDrewDaniel/status/1817910903557570569?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 29, 2024</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

</div></div>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7e7nlauAQ7866PPFMuxtgx?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>HEAL</em>—Machinedrum, AKTHESAVIOR, Deniro Farrar</h3>
<p>Machinedrum’s curatorial efforts on the compilation mentioned above came fresh off the heels of a deluxe LP release. <em>3FOR82_D3LUX3</em> brings even more solid cuts to the table than the original release from back in the spring and this track found me again at the right time in life to embed itself deeply in my rotation. It’s been over 10 years since the <em>Vapor City</em> era and somehow this guy is still finding new things to execute very well. I enjoy the range of experimentation in his crossovers into black music. Not everything hits for me—e.g. I don’t <em>dislike</em> the Jesse Boykins III collaborations, but it’s easy to find R&amp;B I’m more fond of. <em>Kane Train</em> with Freddy Gibbs (2020) was a smash by comparison; a definitive step up in Machinedrum’s ability to find a pocket in hip-hop production with vocal features. <em>HEAL</em> (2024) takes that deeper than production and performance into the realm of transcendent emotional appeal. It’s perhaps a tad less instrumentally inventive but still exquisitely arranged, sitting behind the vocal where it needs to yet still placing melodic variation and dynamic highs where they fit best. Stellar and moving vocal performance and message: life is hard… find a way to push through.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Vz1AtKebBGUyQm6O77Yan?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Lullaby</em>—TURQUOISEDEATH</h3>
<p>I’ve been riding around at night a lot with TURQUOISEDEATH. I’d comfortably put <em>Kaleidoscope</em> in the 2024 sleepers category; definitely unexpected replay value. Solid balance of ethereal ambiance, danceable tempos, and pedal to the metal breakbeat-filled DnB/jungle-esque goodness—not terribly novel, but thoroughly enjoyable.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1NKyiSyZyvz6mHgB4KSKbb?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>
<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Jan+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /><published>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" alt="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /></p>

<p class="mt-200">Ever wished you could hack your sleep schedule, beat jetlag, or stay sharp through an all-nighter without feeling like a zombie? Enter propranolol—a seemingly ordinary beta blocker with some extraordinary tricks up its sleeve. From calming anxiety to resetting your internal clock, propranolol might just be the secret weapon you've been looking for to take control of your sleep and energy levels.</p>

<div class="mv-200 divider-thin"></div>

<h2 id="overview-of-beta-blockers">Overview of beta blockers</h2>

<h3 id="mechanism-of-action">Mechanism of action</h3>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<h3 id="beta-blocker-subtypes">Beta blocker subtypes</h3>

<p>Cardioselective beta blockers mainly work on the heart by blocking beta-1 receptors, which helps lower heart rate and blood pressure. Because they focus more on the heart, they don’t affect the lungs as much, making them safer for people with breathing problems like asthma or COPD.</p>

<p>Non-selective beta blockers block both beta-1 and beta-2 receptors. Since beta-2 receptors are found in the lungs, blood vessels, and muscles, these drugs can affect more than just the heart. This can cause side effects like tightening of the airways, making them less safe for people with asthma or COPD.</p>

<h3 id="applications-for-anxiety">Applications for Anxiety</h3>

<p>This mechanism is particularly beneficial for individuals with social anxiety or general anxiety disorders, as it mitigates physical symptoms of anxiety.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="propranolol-specifics">Propranolol specifics</h2>

<p>Propranolol is a non-selective beta blocker. It is the most lipophilic (fat-soluble) among them, which enables it to cross the blood-brain barrier more effectively.</p>

<h3 id="effects-on-circadian-rhythm">Effects on circadian rhythm</h3>

<p>When propranolol crosses into the brain, it affects the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) in a way that mimics morning blue light exposure. This can lower the body’s natural production of melatonin, which might lead to insomnia and nightmares.</p>

<h3 id="application">Application</h3>

<p>Propranolol can be used to intentionally reduce melatonin production, making it easier to stay awake longer, such as when pulling an all-nighter. It can also be used to reset a chronically desynchronized sleep schedule or overcome jetlag.</p>

<h2 id="example-reversing-a-nocturnal-routine">Example: reversing a nocturnal routine</h2>

<h3 id="background">Background</h3>

<p>Drue Wetsel, a 25-year-old software engineer, has been stuck in a nocturnal routine, habitually falling asleep at 5 am and waking up around 1 pm. He wants to reset his sleep schedule to fall asleep at midnight and wake up at 8 am to align better with a more typical workday and improve his overall health.</p>

<h3 id="circadian-reset-protocol">Circadian reset protocol</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>5 am:</strong> Drue goes to bed at his usual time and sets an alarm for 8 am, planning to get only 3 hours of sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>8 am:</strong> He wakes up, takes propranolol, and uses caffeine to power through the day on minimal sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 pm – 6 pm:</strong> Drue keeps himself busy and alert, using a brief NSDR (non-sleep deep rest) session to avoid napping and maintain energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 am:</strong> Exhausted, Drue finally goes to bed at his new target bedtime, setting an alarm for 8 am to reinforce the new schedule.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Following days:</strong> Drue sticks to the midnight-to-8 am sleep schedule, using propranolol and mild stimulants as needed, until it becomes his new norm.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="additional-medical-applications">Additional medical applications</h2>

<p><strong>Thyroid storm management:</strong> Propranolol helps manage dangerously fast heart rate and high blood pressure caused by excessive thyroid hormone by slowing down the heart and easing other symptoms like anxiety and tremors.</p>

<p><strong>Prevention of cardiac remodeling:</strong> propranolol can help prevent changes in heart structure caused by heart failure (however, other beta blockers are more commonly used for this purpose).</p>

<p><strong>Prophylactic use in cirrhotics:</strong> variceal bleeding occurs when swollen veins in the esophagus or stomach burst and bleed due to liver disease. Non-selective beta blockers like propranolol help prevent this by reducing pressure in those veins.</p>

<p><strong>Treatment of essential tremors:</strong> essential tremors cause uncontrollable shaking, often in the hands. Propranolol helps reduce this shaking, making it easier for people to do everyday tasks.</p>

<h2 id="cautions-and-side-effects">Cautions and side effects</h2>

<p><strong>Respiratory concerns:</strong> propranolol and other non-selective beta blockers can exacerbate asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In conclusion, propranolol is a versatile non-selective beta blocker with a range of applications, from managing anxiety and essential tremors to preventing serious complications in conditions like thyroid storm and cirrhosis. Its ability to cross the blood-brain barrier makes it particularly effective for altering circadian rhythms, offering a solution for those needing to reset their sleep schedules. However, caution is necessary, especially for individuals with respiratory conditions, as propranolol can exacerbate issues like asthma and COPD. Consult a healthcare professional for guidance before using propranolol.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p><a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Circadian+Rhythm+Alteration+with+Propranolol.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you enjoyed this post or if you’ve got any corrections I should know about. Special thanks to <a href="https://substack.com/@quixoteknight">quixoteknight</a> for enriching this post with invaluable insights into medical pharmacology. Read what they have to say about melatonin next.</p>

<h2 class="mt-200 text-center">Related content</h2>
<div class="substack-post-embed" style="margin: 0 auto; border-radius: 12px; overflow: hidden"><p lang="en">Melatonin: MMTYWTK Addendum by QK</p><p>Fun Practical Applications of Abusing Endogenous Neurohormones</p><a data-post-link="" href="https://optimizeeverything.substack.com/p/melatonin-mmtywtk-addendum">Read on Substack</a></div>
<script async="" src="https://substack.com/embedjs/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday and [quixoteknight](https://substack.com/@quixoteknight)</name></author><category term="health" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="sleep" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reset your sleep clock or beat jetlag with beta blockers]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>