<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-11-17T18:29:46-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stedman Halliday</title><subtitle>Stedman Halliday is a technical generalist based in San Francisco creating values-aligned products, brands, media, and experiences.</subtitle><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: May 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/29/7-songs-may-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: May 2025" /><published>2025-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-29T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/29/7-songs-may-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/29/7-songs-may-2025"><![CDATA[<h3><em>Xkyrgios</em>—Evian Christ</h3>

<p>Evian Christ thrives on elevating sound design in electronic music, weaving between the familiar and alien. <em>Xkyrgios</em> continues his exploration of atmospheric textures and unconventional rhythmic structures, building tension through restraint. The approach feels architectural, each element deliberately placed, contributing to a larger sonic structure that reveals itself slowly.</p>

<p>The track embodies the kind of forward-thinking electronic music that doesn’t announce its innovations loudly but instead lets them emerge through careful listening. Evian Christ understands that the most compelling electronic music often happens in the gaps between genres, and <em>Xkyrgios</em> occupies that space with confidence and purpose in a way that feels worthy of a soundtrack.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/08jhfamzypo9XCL5gncI9e?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Gimme Half</em>—The Devil Wears Prada</h3>

<p><em>Gimme Half</em> makes this month’s list in recognition of Daniel Williams: longtime drummer of The Devil Wears Prada who perished in a sudden plane crash a week ago. I learned to drum along to this track and many of the others on <em>With Roots Above and Branches Below</em>. Williams just smacks the kit almost all the way through; the momentum is aggressive and many of the rolling fills are very stimulating to play.</p>

<p>The record represents an apotheosis of aughts metalcore’s more melodic and commercial flavors in both style and production. Roots is pretty much a snapshot of the moment immediately before Joey Sturgis’s Foundation sound felt overproduced and more artificial than ideally maximal. Clean vocals are quite tuned, studio arrangement doesn’t let up often, and the drums are triggered almost to hell, but retain enough feel to punch through very satisfactorily. This LP turns those knobs about as high as they can go before listenability dives sharply—I’m looking forward to banging out a full playthrough in a newly renovated drum room in honor of Daniel. Anyone who’s encouraged me to play more music deserves that tribute.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1jBfKLo7PdlRqMHXTsbgcz?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>World Speed</em>—Yung Skrrt</h3>

<p>Yung Skrrt has been sitting in a lane all his own for a long time: fiercely independent, wildly syncretic, and unapologetically individual. Maybe sonic exploration this broad and unfiltered is a natural consequence of embracing production as a live performance: Skrrt cuts about a thousand tracks a year in front of a livestream audience on <a href="https://www.twitch.tv/yungskrrt">Twitch</a>, streaming every single day (he’s live as I’m writing this). It’s clear that the man’s primary reason for making at this point is for his own entertainment and appreciation, and that’s special.</p>

<p>Plenty of Skrrt’s work falls back on a tried and true formula, but there are so many nuggets of novelty sprinkled throughout his very expansive catalog. It’s clear from his live-produciton broadcasts that his approach is more gestural than compositional and prioritizes feel despite being very fundamentally digital—the man really <em>plays</em> the laptop. Throw a literal fortune wheel of genre into the process and you get some deliciously unexpected moments. Some hit immediately, others grow on you over time, some get recycled in a place they fit much better… it’s like Yung Skrrt’s process and music are a sonic clearinghouse for a plethora of ideas that work in more tightly curated releases. More often than some might expect, he is your favorite producer’s favorite producer.</p>

<p><em>World Speed</em> has some real earworm qualities for these reasons. It’s on one of Skrrt’s <em>Half Words</em> projects which play fast and loose with partial lyrical motifs crooned through heavy autotune that would be more at home in an Internet parody of a Playboi Carti reference track. It keeps the listener in a state of keeping up right from the moment a jarring tone cluster blows through a traditional shimmering synth intro characteristic of a Skrrt track. The 808 pattern on this one is something else entirely. I didn’t like it at first but I kept revisiting it in an attempt to wrap my head around syncopation so zany that it feels like a polyrhythmic locomotive. It got its hooks into me and I can’t get enough of it now. Who would do this in a song and why? Which other artist is punching in with bars about sipping yerba mate like a double cup? This guy is utterly peerless; true one of one.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6BW3kWQwfRJJI4o5ClC9cu?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Genie on My Back</em>—ICYTWAT</h3>

<p>ICYTWAT’s sound is tough and ethereal at the same time in a way that’s frequently hypnotic. The haunting minor string melodies on this track sound right out of a medieval RPG or a title like <em>Silent Hill</em> while the drums knock with a kick that can make a room shake. Perfect soundtrack to lift or walk around to when I can’t bring myself to care about anything at all.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/21NNBt9HGFvivLmTCFUZGe?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Childhood</em>—Kensuke Ushio</h3>

<p>There’s something simply moving about the way that Kensuke Ushio approaches emotional storytelling through sound. <em>Childhood</em> carries the same delicate weight as many of his other iconic soundtracks as a piece that feels like memory itself: fragile, nostalgic, and achingly beautiful.</p>

<p>Ushio’s background in both classical piano and electronic music shines through here. The track manages to be both intimate and expansive, capturing something universal about the bittersweet nature of looking back. It’s the kind of composition that makes you pause whatever you’re doing and just listen as it picks up a click tempo an swings around to its gently swelling resolution.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6e22PmNxZbDR3N8JMe7EvD?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Feather (feat. Cise Starr &amp; Akin from CYNE)</em>—Nujabes</h3>

<p>Musicians who have perished in transportation accidents seems to be a spurious theme this month. Few producers have left as indelible a mark on hip-hop as Nujabes, and <em>Feather</em> stands as one of his most enduring achievements. The way he weaves jazz samples into something entirely new while maintaining respect for both traditions is nothing short of masterful. Cise Starr and Akin deliver verses that feel like conversations with old friends—thoughtful, unpretentious, and deeply human.</p>

<p>The track embodies everything that made Nujabes special: the ability to create music that’s simultaneously nostalgic and forward-thinking, complex and accessible, serious and joyful. More than fifteen years after his passing, <em>Feather</em> still feels like a blueprint for how to honor musical heritage while pushing it into new territory. I’m grateful to my friend Russel for <a href="https://x.com/rslantonie/status/1927335213668983123">priming a full listen of <em>Modal Soul</em></a> as I walked the streets of downtown Chicago in the morning.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2ej1A2Ze6P2EOW7KfIosZR?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Right Now</em>—Mario Abney</h3>

<p>I was pleasurably introduced to Mario Abney’s music at the 50th anniversary show for Andy’s Jazz Club in Chicago where he and his band played with New Orleans legend Donald Harrison Jr. Abney has cultivated a jazz sensibility that feels both rooted in tradition and unafraid to explore new territory. <em>Right Now</em> showcases his ability to create music that’s sophisticated without being pretentious, accessible without being simple. There’s a spiritual quality to the composition that suggests deeper currents running beneath the surface.</p>

<p>The track works on multiple levels—as a showcase for technical skill, as an emotional journey, and as a piece of music that simply feels good to experience. Abney understands that the best jazz has always been about communication, and <em>Right Now</em> is a conversation worth joining right from the beginning as his trumpet talks to a saxophone.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0GbxeWWv8cuc20Bg5V6KZU?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+May+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: May 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/26/selected-quotes-may-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: May 2025" /><published>2025-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-05-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/26/selected-quotes-may-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/05/26/selected-quotes-may-2025"><![CDATA[<h2 id="theodore-n-vail-on-difficulty">Theodore N. Vail on difficulty</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Real difficulties can be overcome; it is only the imaginary ones that are unconquerable.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Theodore N. Vail</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="paul-kalanithi-on-perseverance">Paul Kalanithi on perseverance</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I can’t go on. I’ll go on.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Paul Kalanithi, <em>When Breath Becomes Air</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="musashi-miyamoto-on-triumph">Musashi Miyamoto on triumph</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Today is victory over yourself of yesterday; tomorrow is your victory over lesser men.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Musashi Miyamoto, <em>The Book of Five Rings</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+May+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Apr 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/28/7-songs-apr-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Apr 2025" /><published>2025-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-28T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/28/7-songs-apr-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/28/7-songs-apr-2025"><![CDATA[<h3 id="wash2jon-bellion"><em>WASH2</em>—Jon Bellion</h3>

<p>It’s a rare and refreshing thing these days to hear an artist capable of spanning both maximalist pop production and the raw immediacy of stripped-down performance. On <em>WASH2</em>, Jon Bellion dials it all the way back—just voice and piano—and the result is quietly devastating. <em>WASH</em> adds that pop instrumentation and production, but the songwriting and voice on this alternate take are powerful enough to carry all the weight.</p>

<p>Jon’s upcoming album drops in June, and if recent releases and the trailer are any indication, it’s going to be something special. It’s good to see him back and flexing range in a way that still feels grounded.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7hzak3sRAXxzoU4cOXFSjt?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<figure class="mt-100">
    <style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style><div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/-0lXs1tSJPI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
    <figcaption>FATHER FIGURE (Stadium Trailer)</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Deal</em>—Organ Tapes, 500</h3>

<p>I’ve been focusing on vocal production recently in the studio, so I’m listening to vocals with a lot more attention than usual. I’m getting a lot out of a careful ear on tracks where more emphasis is on vibe than vocal performance. Organ Tapes embraces subdued delivery in this way, but I’m emulating a good amount of production technique when it comes to using space in captivating ways: doubling and octaves, different delay and reverb plays on wet vocal chains, panning and tremolo, unique automation throws, etc. There are a lot of fun sounds in here and it’s a nice, relaxed track to skate slowly and carve to when the sun’s out.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/283YMjj2Q6R2C8hKcFDiQb?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>SCREAM</em>—MIKE DEAN</h3>

<p>I’ve come to admire Mike Dean as something like the anti-Rick Rubin. Like Rubin, he’s an industry veteran in his sixties who has dutifully earned his place on hip-hop’s Mount Rushmore of behind-the-scenes architects many times over. But instead of prominently projecting sagely aura, Dean maintains a low profile and a blunt on him at all times. Where Rubin has sported a bald crown with hair on the sides and a Zeus beard, Dean has at times opted for the exact opposite haircut. Rubin claims not to play any instruments (at least adeptly), whereas Dean has at least once casually blurted out that he’s classically trained in a way that seems almost accidental and somewhat antithetical to his image and comportment.</p>

<p>Dean plays multiple instruments but is best known for his analog synth work, often being called the Synth God. Lately, he’s taken to livestreaming his studio improv sessions from a room packed with synths, occasionally shaping those jams into full LPs. His annual <em>420</em> releases collect these moments: expansive, moody, often surprisingly listenable between things. <em>SCREAM</em> is one of the cuts that leans harder into energy. The synths are melodic, dynamic, and gritty in relief against the chill yet incisive drums. Always nice when the Synth God decides to raise his voice a little.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1lQNdXccNyaq4Gsxz3mwMO?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Stylo</em>—Gorillaz feat. Mos Def and Bobby Womack</h3>

<p>Another track with a driving rhythm, synth attack, and an iconic wail. There’s something I really admire about how the bones of Damon Albarn’s process still show through in much of his finished work. You can feel the core loop, the drum machine, the simple idea at its heart, and yet the final product emerges as something entirely fresh, built through sonic iteration and Albarn’s trademark genre syncretism. <em>Stylo</em> is a great example of that sensibility. The hypnotic refrain from Mos Def and the searing, soulful chorus from Bobby Womack take what could have been a mechanical groove and give it emotional life.</p>

<p>There’s an Apple Music interview from a couple years back that captures this simple songwriting approach. Albarn walks Zane Lowe through a studio and casually demos how <em>Clint Eastwood</em> came to be. He reveals that Gorillaz’s breakout single from over two decades ago was basically pulled straight off of the first preset on a Suzuki Omnichord. It doesn’t make the song any worse, as the decisive transformations between that loop and the final track are a masterful way to drive home the idea that simplicity can become greatness. It’s a good reminder that great songs don’t need to be complex—they just need a spark, and the willingness to follow it.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6LUfuyLgvgqrykiTE6sJHY?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<figure class="mt-100">
    <div class="grid col2" style="grid-template-columns: 1fr 1fr">
        <img src="/assets/img/2025-04-28-omnichord-0.jpg" alt="Suzuki Omnichord OM-108" />
        <img src="/assets/img/2025-04-28-omnichord-1.jpg" alt="Suzuki Omnichord OM-108" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>Suzuki Omnichord OM-108</figcaption>
    <div class="mt-100">
        <style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style><div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/EDX6l9_58RA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
    </div>
    <figcaption>Damon Albarn &amp; Zane Lowe</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Alba del orate</em>—The Mars Volta</h3>

<p>The Mars Volta’s new record is full of surprises. It moves through jazz, pop, and Latin metal with a fluidity that’s hard to pin down. <em>Alba del orate</em> stands out. The gradual transition into double-timey polyrhythmic jazz percussion and the sudden attack of wobbling saw waves are exciting.</p>

<p>This album feels like a continuous current, flowing from one track to the next with a mix of uncanny cohesion and unexpected turns. There’s something thrilling about how much ground it covers while still feeling so focused. I don’t know what I expected from a new Mars Volta release in 2025, but I’m glad to have heard something that makes it feel like album craft is not a lost art.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3W8kTyO5WuQORyptg0kYR5?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Black Dunes (Woman in the Dunes Mix)</em>—This Will Destroy You, Holy Other</h3>

<p><em>Tunnel Blanket</em> is an instrumental record that’s among my favorites, having stood the test of time for nearly 15 years now. Coming in at nearly an hour, it’s a long-form meditative journey through psychedelic transcendence that’s as comforting in some pockets as it is challenging in others. Holy Other’s take on the penultimate track condenses its length considerably and breathes new life and rhythm into it (especially with the crescendo beneath staccato synth leads at the end) while preserving and enhancing the original track’s atmosphere using signature vocal sampling technique.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/5yYz39nEuOXpNir7FSB8rA?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Mouse Policy</em>—Cloud Nothings</h3>

<p><em>Mouse Policy</em> barrels forward with Cloud Nothings channelling some of the urgency and youthful garage rock energy that made me fall in love with <em>Attack on Memory</em> back in 2012, but it’s tempered now. It’s more patient and layered with still simple yet more refined songwriting. The chorus soars while the outro glows with a wistful and nostalgic post-rock sparkle.</p>

<p><em>Final Summer</em> is an apt title for this full-length release from last year. Listening to it makes me feel like I’m back in college for a moment: still figuring everything out, still angry for no good reason, still subtly puppeteered by the idea that guitars could save me.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4wW5MeIK2XxXDKWRP2WWy0?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Apr+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-04-28-omnichord-0.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-04-28-omnichord-0.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Apr 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/19/selected-quotes-apr-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Apr 2025" /><published>2025-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/19/selected-quotes-apr-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/04/19/selected-quotes-apr-2025"><![CDATA[<h2 id="mike-tyson-on-humility">Mike Tyson on humility</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>If you’re not humble, life will visit humbleness upon you.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Mike Tyson</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="mark-twain-on-humility">Mark Twain on humility</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I was gratified to be able to answer promptly, and I did. I said I didn’t know.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Mark Twain</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="archbishop-desmond-tutu-on-humility">Archbishop Desmond Tutu on humility</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Humility allows us to celebrate the gifts of others, but it does not mean you have to deny your own gifts or shrink from using them.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Archbishop Desmond Tutu, <em>The Book of Joy</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Apr+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Mar 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/31/7-songs-mar-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Mar 2025" /><published>2025-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-31T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/31/7-songs-mar-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/31/7-songs-mar-2025"><![CDATA[<h3 id="tears-in-heaveneric-clapton"><em>Tears in Heaven</em>—Eric Clapton</h3>

<p>I can never quite predict the lessons I’ll come away from grief with. What seems true over time is that those lessons become easier to learn and that I grow in my ability to accept and process them more readily (even if some fighting and difficulty are involved). For the last few months, loss is something that has been more salient than I’d ideally like it to be, but I’m emerging from it as a stronger person with a more reassured and independent sense of self. I’m grateful for the transformation brought about by having known someone who is now gone; someone that has always been there for as long as I can remember and will now continue to be there, albeit in a different way.</p>

<p><em>Tears in Heaven</em> is a tune with grief at its core: Clapton’s tragic memorial of his son gone too soon after tumbling through a window at the tender age of four. The forlorn longing in his voice is palpable when he pleadingly asks if his deceased boy would know his name should they meet in heaven. I’m not sure things like that matter to me now—I have known and will remember her name in this life and I am better for it.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1kgdslQYmeTR4thk9whoRw?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Self/Less</em>—Alecia Creti</h3>

<p>I featured a track from Gallant in <a href="/blog/2025/02/19/7-songs-feb-2025">last month’s 7 Songs</a> and mentioned I’d had a chance to watch him perform live for the first time in a while at the Independent in San Francisco. Alecia Creti opened for him at that show and it was wonderful to get acquainted with her music alongside her detailed narratives about each number on her setlist. Her vocal performance was astounding and her simultaneous piano accompaniment intimate and moving.</p>

<p>Despite occasionally surfacing twinges of emotional immaturity, her interstitial monologues painted an authentic and endearing portrait of a young artist in the midst of experiencing their dreams come to fruition and developing a stronger sense of self that manifests powerfully in their craft. <em>Self/Less</em> is a track about having the courage and strength to put oneself first when doing so seems to run counter to duty to others (namely family). That theme resonated with me powerfully as I stood in the audience while Alecia belted the words.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7358J7q6CvnvVPui2ogvlE?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>magnetic</em>—UMI</h3>

<p>I remember a lot about the first time I heard <em>Forest in the City</em> years ago. It was a very fitting record to sulk to as I left the place I call home in a sense more final than ever before—my love for someone receding; unmaintanable in the face of timing, circumstance, and the different ways life tends to work out for different people. <em>magnetic</em> potently highlights that contrast between yearning and realism: love, however broad and deep, isn’t always sufficient to ensure its own preservation.</p>

<p>While once a deeply sad listen, the shape of melancholy it brings forth is different now. It’s about having had the privilege to love, gaining the wisdom to know that sharing a life with someone is about more than feelings, and growing enough to let go of being drawn to someone when that needs to happen to make room for more life.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/64tHsFnlwPJucfb6ohkkRt?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>On a Mountain Under Full Moon</em>—Wicca Phase Springs Eternal feat. Fantasy Camp</h3>

<p>Adam McIlwee sings like a boy with a sometimes magical and other times painful, yet always rich inner world who’s frequently catching himself in the middle of urban or rural nowhere, wistfully appreciating the mysteries of the universe… and I <em>get</em> that. The importance of regarding the moon—full or otherwise—should not be discounted, whether on a mountain or on the range. The outro’s acoustic guitar harmonics with time-stretched reverse delay are a great example of doing a lot with a little. Gestures like that inspire novel approaches to my own arrangements.</p>

<p>More on letting go as a lyrical theme in this one, much of it from the Fantasy Camp feature:</p>

<p><em>It’s the mystery I’m after</em><br />
<em>It’s the magic I believe in</em><br />
<em>On a mountain under full moon</em><br />
<em>I can say goodnight and mean it</em></p>

<p><em>But if you ever really loved me</em><br />
<em>You would say goodnight and set me free</em></p>

<p><em>So don’t you worry ‘bout me</em><br />
<em>I kinda like this feeling</em><br />
<em>I’m the master of my own world</em><br />
<em>Riding into the evening</em></p>

<figure>
    <div class="grid col2" style="grid-template-rows: auto auto">
        <img style="grid-row: 1 / 3" alt="present nowhere" src="/assets/img/2025-03-31-present-nowhere_01.webp" />
        <img alt="present nowhere" src="/assets/img/2025-03-31-present-nowhere_02.webp" />
        <img alt="present nowhere" src="/assets/img/2025-03-31-present-nowhere_03.webp" />
    </div>
    <figcaption>Thanks Megan. Thanks Dan.</figcaption>
</figure>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7ENs0e9ZM3azBKM58lDM47?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Heaven Will Come</em>—Tim Hecker</h3>

<p>Tim Hecker’s sonic landscaping feels inextricably focused on evoking the divine, giving equal attention to both its heavenly and haunting auras. If there ever were an assurance that heaven will come, it can be found in reverberating organ progressions textured and modulated with the signatures of careful Max patchwork.</p>

<p>It’s another great soundtrack for momentary nowheres—time between events, space between places that become holy sites unto themselves in newfound ways. Appreciating ambient music conditions an appreciation of being with spaciousness. In Hecker’s work, that spaciousness is a divine void that shifts between light and dark, warm and cool, this world and another. Perhaps here, it can be a shift between the darker sides of grief and the room for something newer and brighter that lies beyond.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4XL9nn0qDcLA25X88wxmrw?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>A Greater Love</em>—Yves Tumor</h3>

<p><em>A Greater Love</em> is the moody and ethereal conclusion to 2020’s <em>Heaven To A Tortured Mind</em>. It’s a song about change: the change in the seasons, the weather, and the emotions and connections that shift as time has its way with all of us. The power of loss to change us for the better—to beneficially reshape our relationships with others and with ourselves—is an under-acknowledged silver lining of grief.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3u3kKwR4TgxtPxJFvVWn7F?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>道 (Michi)</em>—Hikaru Utada</h3>

<p>Human beings, narratively obsessed as we are, tend to hope that the culmination of grieving heralds a return to normalcy and perhaps even greener pastures beyond: a road to thriving in greater wholeness. Utada’s <em>道 (Michi)</em>—<em>road</em> in English—draws the contours of that road. It’s the opening track on 2016’s <em>Fantôme</em>: a return from a lengthy hiatus, and a record that Utada takes particular pride in: “[<em>Fantôme</em>] marked the beginning of a new chapter of my life as an artist and as a human being.”</p>

<p>The track and the album as a whole surfaced meditations on loss and grief in the wake of the artist’s mother’s tragic suicide. The chorus offers an enduring reminder that we can be lonely, yet not alone; that life can be grieved but also celebrated and that it can give birth to new life, much like Utada’s career beginnings were inspired by her mother’s musicianship.</p>

<p>It is in 2024’s <em>Science Fiction</em> compilation album that <em>Michi</em> finds new life of its own, still an upbeat and danceable standout even amidst collaborations with A.G. Cook and Floating Points. It was seemingly a happier time for Utada, marking the 25th anniversary of her debut while she raises a child of her own (also featured on the album). I think that’s how I’d like to end this month’s list: with an upbeat and hopeful reflection on what’s possible after grief subsides.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4H8iChdvjdsxrxSAVi9Wy1?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Mar+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-03-31-present-nowhere_03.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-03-31-present-nowhere_03.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Mar 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/11/selected-quotes-mar-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Mar 2025" /><published>2025-03-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-03-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/11/selected-quotes-mar-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/03/11/selected-quotes-mar-2025"><![CDATA[<h2 id="andre-agassi-on-self-defined-success">Andre Agassi on self-defined success</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I’ve been cheered by thousands, booed by thousands, but nothing feels as bad as the booing inside your own head during those ten minutes before you fall asleep.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Andre Agassi, <em>Open</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="john-wooden-on-acceptance-and-optimism">John Wooden on acceptance and optimism</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Things work out best for those who make the best of how things work out.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—John Wooden</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="viktor-frankl-on-the-power-of-choice">Viktor Frankl on the power of choice</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Between stimulus and response there is a space. In that space is our power to choose our response. In our response lies our growth and our freedom.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Viktor Frankl</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Mar+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Feb 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/19/7-songs-feb-2025" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Feb 2025" /><published>2025-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-19T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/19/7-songs-feb-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/19/7-songs-feb-2025"><![CDATA[<h3 id="kid-againjon-bellion"><em>KID AGAIN</em>—Jon Bellion</h3>

<p>A friend put me onto this track back in November after hearing my guitar noodling reminded him of the intro loop and it hasn’t left my rotation for long since. Jon Bellion’s triumphant return with a first solo track in six years is equal parts melodic and aggressive, with a driving energy that reminds me what it’s like to keep trying to get back to the feeling of being a kid again, cooking things up in my bedroom.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0FcVZWtHJ0XoHhbT8fiyAg?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Red Synthetic</em>—Zhone</h3>

<p>My second pick of the month isn’t a new track, but I come back to Zhone’s <em>Red Synthetic</em> frequently. Sonically, there’s a ton to appreciate about it: huge, cinematic dynamics and sound design and that moment just past the halfway mark where the filter EQ sweeps down on the vocal refrain to yield something like a vocoder synth. This track’s release notably calls forth the spirit of this post series: music discovery through the lens of first-person experience. There’s something special about the way online music discovery in particular evolved over the decade leading up to this release in 2021. I used to usually discover music online through the blogosphere, but by the height of the pandemic, I found myself in niche online communities communicating and collaborating with artists, sharing work in its early stages.</p>

<p>I first heard this track when Zhone shared a pre-release version in Outskrrts, an online community that broke out of <a href="twitch.tv/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt’s Twitch stream</a> during the pandemic to organize events like stream pregames, afterparty raves, and artist showcases, all over Zoom. The release later found a home on Vol. 4 (<em>LOVE</em>) of the <em>Mutants</em> Mixtape series of benefit compilations, themselves a product of a niche online community of artists: the <a href="https://discord.com/invite/RnSWscwmaw">Mutants1000000 Discord</a> launched by Arca right as the world went into lockdown in March of 2020. I cherish the special connections that are still in my life from my time in these communities and hold sacred the opportunity to observe artists’ nascent work as they share stories behind it.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4RCpC8oxbkqZRwidTkjgRv?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Blue Hour</em>—Nosaj Thing feat. Julianna Barwick</h3>

<p>A couple of months ago, I caught a special performance featuring Nosaj Thing at the Audrey Irmas Pavilion in Koreatown. The venue itself is a marvel—geometric and imposing, yet somehow inviting, like a monument to the modern. The night was a layered experience: an exhibition upstairs featuring art and technology experiments, followed by <a href="https://www.kevinpeterhe.com/flux"><em>Flux,</em></a> a collaboration between Kevin Peter He and Jake Oleson that blended live music with real-time 3D cinematics and dynamic camera work. It was a fluid, maximalist vision of what’s possible at the intersection of sound and image.</p>

<p>Afterward, Nosaj Thing took the stage, framed by simple film projections—subtle, restrained, evocative. After the hypermodern spectacle of <em>Flux,</em> his set felt like a meditation, pulling attention toward nostalgia rather than novelty. <em>Blue Hour</em> in particular hit me in that way—like something slipping through my fingers, a fleeting warmth held just long enough to feel its absence. The visuals accompanying it had a liminal, in-between quality—scenes that could be anywhere and nowhere, the kind of images that bring to mind times caught in the cracks of a city, existing but untethered, anonymous in the early hours of the morning.</p>

<p>Watching Nosaj Thing in LA again some 15 years after first seeing him perform at Low End Theory was a full-circle moment. That era still lingers in my head like a half-remembered dream… and that’s exactly what the city looked like as I stepped outside into the rainy night to find some casein.</p>

<figure style="display: grid; grid-template-columns: auto auto; grid-gap: 32px">
    <img alt="Audrey Irmas Pavillion" src="/assets/img/2025-02-19-audrey-irmas-pavillion.jpg" />
    <img alt="spooky parking lot" src="/assets/img/2025-02-19-plot.jpg" />
</figure>

<iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6f9BnONLZr0rpB5thUzzlW?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Curves</em>—Ivy Lab</h3>

<p><em>Curves</em> by Ivy Lab also feels like a transmission from the late aughts LA Beat Scene: Low End Theory, Shlohmo, the WEDIDIT crew, etc. The track vibes in a lush space between ambient ethereality and club weight, where textures stretch and morph into something atmospheric and trip-hop sensibilities meet sculpted bass design. This sound isn’t terribly new anymore, but here it seems to remain pure as a hypnotic loop bending time around its pulses. It’s a solid reminder of similar sounds from the past, still echoing and resonating.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/14gFoEG2vJmqM7LaYRJ49m?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Fellow Traveler</em>—Fucked Up</h3>

<p><em>Fellow Traveler</em> kicks off with a reversing tape loop that winds back time just before the a wildly distorted riff tears through the mix. The call-and-response vocals layer in tasteful harmonies that offer a kind of rough singsong quality. It’s a song with driving force that never stops moving, bursting with a restless, youthful energy that makes me want to run outside and keep running until the last note fades.</p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6OGg4W6YQ0VO7SOvWvYLV8?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Subversion (Brand New Love)</em>—Touché Amoré feat. Lou Barlow</h3>

<p>The guys in Touché are approaching (if not already within) their middle age years (frontman Jeremy Bolm now boasts 41 years of age). That’s a sobering realization. I’m not quite there yet myself, but it’s been more than half my lifetime since I started watching them play small rooms in LA and I won’t lie, I’m starting to feel the clock. What better opportunity to interpolate Sebadoh’s <em>Brand New Love</em>—a song about cautious hope and openness to something new (<em>anyone could be a brand new love</em>)—alongside original lyricist Lou Barlow. Bolm’s refrain says it best:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I can’t see</em><br />
<em>Beyond the</em><br />
<em>Years behind me</em><br />
<em>And it’s staggering</em></p>
</blockquote>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2Yc1uDPTWtZtQdOYdCdmYl?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Bourbon</em>—Gallant</h3>

<p>Earlier this month, I had the chance to see Gallant perform at the Independent in San Francisco on tour for his latest release <em>Zinc</em>. His always stellar performance made for a fun show where I ran into old friends and made some new ones. Some fans I chatted with expressed a lingering preference for his debut album, <em>Ology</em> (2016), over the newer material (a sentiment I share). While I hope that the soaring falsettos and anthemic delivery on <em>Bourbon</em> gave those fans what they were looking for, I found a lot of appreciation for how the live band instrumentation added dimension to Gallant’s newer material. It was a good reminder that making room for what’s new sometimes means loosening one’s hold on the past—<em>trust the detox.</em></p>

<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3Dp5SHGbRIqjGGI3cPdESA?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Feb+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-02-19-plot.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-02-19-plot.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">skrrtStats 2021–2024</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/12/skrrtstats-2021-2024" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="skrrtStats 2021–2024" /><published>2025-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-12T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/12/skrrtstats-2021-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/12/skrrtstats-2021-2024"><![CDATA[<p>I am undeniably a <a href="https://twitch.tv/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt</a> superfan. There is something (several specific things, actually) about his music that triggers a deep fixation in me with roots as low as the limbic tier. I’ll write a blog post about them someday in honor of the Gimbus GOAT King of Internet Music.</p>

<p>For now, I’ll collate annual analytics for my Yung Skrrt streaming data which I’ve been collecting for four years running. I’ll also share <a href="#diy">my code</a> so you can generate insights from your own Spotify streaming data for your favorite artists.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="skrrtstats-2024">skrrtStats 2024</h2>

<p>51.59 listening hours (2.15 days) for 261 unique tracks</p>

<figure><iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/6hr9d48fg8MQOelqGl4kZE?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe></figure>

<figure>
<img alt="skrrtStats 2024" src="/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2024.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="skrrtstats-2023">skrrtStats 2023</h2>

<p>67.56 listening hours (2.82 days) for 223 unique tracks</p>

<figure><iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/0ha7OKLcawZOxyqVt7Me10?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe></figure>

<figure>
<img alt="skrrtStats 2023" src="/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2023.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="skrrtstats-2022">skrrtStats 2022</h2>

<p>96.50 listening hours (4.02 days) for 223 unique tracks</p>

<figure><iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/4lHoMCeulPnLI0KYSKdfx2?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe></figure>

<figure>
<img alt="skrrtStats 2022" src="/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2022.png" />
</figure>

<h2 id="skrrtstats-2021">skrrtStats 2021</h2>

<p>55.54 listening hours (2.31 days) for 142 unique tracks</p>

<figure><iframe style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1coJjj2WcBxR9k8GvNgwT8?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe></figure>

<figure>
<img alt="skrrtStats 2021" src="/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2021.png" />
</figure>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="diy">Generate your own insights</h2>

<p>Generate insights for any artist of your choice from your own Spotify streaming data. Here’s how:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Visit the Spotify Account privacy page and log in</li>
  <li>Request a copy of your personal data with the Download your data tool
    <ul>
      <li>Use the normal option, not <em>Extended streaming history</em></li>
      <li>It will take some time for Spotify to process your data and email you back with a download link</li>
      <li>Download and unarchive your data</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Download code from <a href="https://gist.github.com/stedmanhalliday/910dbf4fe1193d2849966fe28bbc56c6">this gist</a>, or copy it to a new file from the block below</li>
  <li>Place the script file in the same directory as the unarchived data folder (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Spotify Account Data</code>)</li>
  <li>Edit the constants up top for the artist and number of top tracks you’d like to output</li>
  <li>Run the script from the command line with <a href="https://nodejs.org/en">Node.js</a> or an equivalent JavaScript runtime environment</li>
</ol>

<ul>
  <li>Bonus: use <a href="https://carbon.now.sh/">Carbon</a> to generate cool snapshots of your stats like the ones I’ve featured in this post</li>
</ul>

<figure class="highlight"><pre><code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript"><span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">ARTIST</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">Yung Skrrt</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">;</span>    <span class="c1">// substitute any artist (ensure exact match)</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">TOP_TRACKS</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">;</span>           <span class="c1">// number of top trackx to display</span>

<span class="c1">// time conversion constants</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">MS_IN_HR</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">3600000</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">HRS_IN_DAY</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">24</span><span class="p">;</span>

<span class="c1">// GOTTA HIT THE STORAGE SPOT, GET UP IN THE STASH!</span>
<span class="c1">// retreive and consolidate streaming data</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">streams0</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">./Spotify Account Data/StreamingHistory_music_0.json</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">streams1</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">require</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">./Spotify Account Data/StreamingHistory_music_1.json</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">streams</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">streams0</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">concat</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">streams1</span><span class="p">);</span>

<span class="c1">// filter to streams of tracks by artist</span>
<span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">artistStreams</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">streams</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">filter</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">artistName</span> <span class="o">===</span> <span class="nx">ARTIST</span><span class="p">);</span>

<span class="c1">// return play duration of all artist streams in milliseconds</span>
<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">getDuration</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">duration</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="nx">artistStreams</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nx">duration</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">msPlayed</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">duration</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// return duration in hours</span>
<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">getDurationInHours</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">return </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">getDuration</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">MS_IN_HR</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">round</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// return duration in days</span>
<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">getDurationInDays</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="k">return </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">getDuration</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">MS_IN_HR</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="nx">HRS_IN_DAY</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">round</span><span class="p">();</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// return a sorted (descending) Map&lt;trackName, playCount&gt;</span>
<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">getTracksByPlayCount</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">trackCounts</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Map</span><span class="p">();</span>
    <span class="nx">artistStreams</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">forEach</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="o">!</span><span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">has</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">trackName</span><span class="p">))</span> <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">trackName</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="p">}</span> <span class="k">else</span> <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">count</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">get</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">trackName</span><span class="p">);</span>
            <span class="nx">count</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">;</span>
            <span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">set</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">stream</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">trackName</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">count</span><span class="p">);</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="p">});</span>

    <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">trackRanks</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">Map</span><span class="p">([...</span><span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">entries</span><span class="p">()].</span><span class="nf">sort</span><span class="p">((</span><span class="nx">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">b</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">=&gt;</span> <span class="nx">b</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">-</span> <span class="nx">a</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]));</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">trackRanks</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// return a string listing the first n top tracks</span>
<span class="kd">function</span> <span class="nf">listTopTracks</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">trackCounts</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">getTracksByPlayCount</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nf">entries</span><span class="p">();</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">topTracksList</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="dl">""</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="kd">let</span> <span class="nx">rank</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="k">for </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">track</span> <span class="k">of</span> <span class="nx">trackCounts</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="k">if </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">rank</span> <span class="o">&gt;</span> <span class="nx">TOP_TRACKS</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
            <span class="k">break</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="p">}</span>
        <span class="nx">topTracksList</span> <span class="o">+=</span> <span class="nc">String</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">rank</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">padStart</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">0</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">. </span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span> 
        <span class="nx">track</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="se">\"</span><span class="s2"> with </span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">track</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">]</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2"> plays </span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">;</span>
        <span class="nx">rank</span><span class="o">++</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>

    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">topTracksList</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// decimal rounding (to hundredths)</span>
<span class="nb">Number</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">prototype</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">round</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">const</span> <span class="nx">num</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">;</span>
    <span class="k">return </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nb">Math</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">round</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">num</span> <span class="o">*</span> <span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="mi">100</span><span class="p">).</span><span class="nf">toFixed</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">);</span>
<span class="p">}</span>

<span class="c1">// string formatter</span>
<span class="nb">String</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">prototype</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">format</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kd">function</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="p">{</span>
    <span class="kd">var</span> <span class="nx">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="k">this</span><span class="p">,</span>
        <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">arguments</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nx">length</span><span class="p">;</span>

    <span class="k">while </span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="o">--</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="p">{</span>
        <span class="nx">s</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">replace</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="k">new</span> <span class="nc">RegExp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="se">\\</span><span class="s1">{</span><span class="dl">'</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">i</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="se">\\</span><span class="s1">}</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="dl">'</span><span class="s1">gm</span><span class="dl">'</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="nx">arguments</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="nx">i</span><span class="p">]);</span>
    <span class="p">}</span>
    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="nx">s</span><span class="p">;</span>
<span class="p">};</span>

<span class="c1">// STATS UP, STATS UP!</span>
<span class="c1">// print artist stats</span>
<span class="nx">console</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">log</span><span class="p">(</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span> 
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">You listened to {0} for {1} hours. That's {2} days. </span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">format</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nx">ARTIST</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nf">getDurationInHours</span><span class="p">(),</span> <span class="nf">getDurationInDays</span><span class="p">())</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">You listened to {0} unique {1} songs. </span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">format</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="nf">getTracksByPlayCount</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nx">size</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="nx">ARTIST</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">Your top </span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="nx">ARTIST</span> <span class="o">+</span> <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2"> tracks </span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="s2">--------------------------</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="nf">listTopTracks</span><span class="p">()</span> <span class="o">+</span>
    <span class="dl">"</span><span class="se">\n</span><span class="dl">"</span>
<span class="p">);</span></code></pre></figure>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? Do you have thoughts about Yung Skrrt? Wanna show me what your top artist breakdown looks like? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+skrrtStats+2021%E2%80%932024.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let’s yap about it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="software" /><category term="data" /><category term="code" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Annual analytics for my Yung Skrrt streaming data]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2022.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2025-02-12-skrrtStats-2022.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Feb 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Feb 2025" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hermann-hesse-on-not-reading">Hermann Hesse on <em>not</em> reading</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Stand just once at the stage where the stone by the road means as much to you as Goethe and Tolstoy, you will thereafter gain from Goethe, Tolstoy, and all poets infinitely more value, more sap and honey, more affirmation of life and of yourself than ever before.</em></p>

  <p><em>For the works of Goethe are not Goethe and the volumes of Dostoevsky are not Dostoevsky, they are only an attempt, a dubious and never successful attempt, to conjure up the many-voiced multitudinous world of which he was the central point.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Hermann Hesse, <em>On Reading Books</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="thomas-merton-on-the-yips">Thomas Merton on the yips</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>When an archer is shooting for nothing he has all his skill. If he shoots for a brass buckle he is already nervous. If he shoots for a prize of gold he goes blind or sees two targets—he is out of his mind. His skill has not changed, but the prize divides him. He cares, he thinks more of winning than of shooting—and the need to win drains him of power.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Thomas Merton, <em>The Way of Chuang Tzu</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="seneca-the-younger-on-true-friendship">Seneca the Younger on true friendship</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>One who seeks friendship for favorable occasions strips it of all its nobility.</em></p>

  <p><em>If you consider any man a friend whom you do not trust as you trust yourself, you are mightily mistaken and you do not sufficiently understand what true friendship means… When friendship is settled, you must trust; before friendship is formed, you must pass judgment. Those persons indeed put last first and confound their duties, who… judge a man after they have made him their friend, instead of making him their friend after they have judged him. Ponder for a long time whether you shall admit a given person to your friendship; but when you have decided to admit him, welcome him with all your heart and soul. Speak as boldly with him as with yourself… Regard him as loyal and you will make him loyal.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Seneca the Younger</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Feb+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Jan 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Jan 2025" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs"><![CDATA[<h3><em>Stone Woman Gives Birth To A Child At Night</em>—Mount Eerie</h3>
<p>I’ve spent much of autumn’s turn to winter coasting around California in a sedan. I’m surprised at how long it’s taken me to give the roads their fair due with amount of time I’ve lived in California while owning a car. When Mount Eerie’s been on, I’ve found myself stopping more frequently to contemplate whatever’s knocking at the threshold of my attention—a scenic vista or a mundane slice of time. Awareness has taken on a wide range of flavors from slow and viscous to bold, sweeping, and dynamic. It’s an appropriate soundtrack for being present nowhere in particular.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2xeAZhRIegjVgPyd6Hr4x7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Circles</em>—Thrice</h3>
<p>There’s something I truly appreciate about the way many gems from Thrice’s wide-ranging discography allow themselves <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1879417785857761549">to be found</a> and sat within time and again. <em>Beggars</em> is one of my favorite records and <em>Circles</em> is a highlight that’s equal parts somber and expansive, with a small measure of twinkling hope. The lyrics characterize humans as intrepid yet futile in our perennial quests to cast ourselves into the dark and build upon what we know despite our ultimate ignorance, blindness, and fallibility. I haven’t watched these guys play in over 10 years (since the last dates of their farewell tour pre-reunion); perhaps it’s time to indulge a little nostalgia.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3VppAi6bcWZo9y2Gc0VmPg?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hey Listen</em>—Drug Church</h3>
<p>Drug Church’s <em>Prude</em> was one of my favorite releases of 2024. It doesn’t break much new ground sonically, but the songs are well written despite their structural and lyrical simplicity. The tracklist is built with vignettes—often crushing ones—of life on the other side of cracks in modern life that many people would rather just pretend aren’t there (along with the people who’ve fallen through them). Hearing <em>Hey Listen</em> reminds me of an unlucky kid I used to get into trouble with when I was running low on luck myself. It makes me feel abruptly anxious and awfully guilty; sapped and resigned to abject cowardice, shame, and disappointment, yet ultimately grateful. It is indeed tough to find an upside, but there’s no hope for luck without the intent to search. Thanks to <a href="https://x.com/em32label/status/1885020104917954783">Carlos Jarquin</a> for listening to me yap about sad shit. <a href="https://forms.gle/Dt7X7wBvobb9cPdC7">Go tell him</a> about a song that means something to you.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1lwgbuHay1ujrTepc28fck?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hollywood</em>—Toro y Moi, Benjamin Gibbard</h3>
<p>The end of last year saw me falling back into old patterns of landing myself in some total bullshit in Hollywood. Changing—truly and permanently changing—is a tall order. I guess I’m working my way up to it, but it’s really nobody’s business to even try to help me with this stuff anymore. On an entirely separate note, instrumental production is resonating with me here as creative inspiration. I’m sitting on several years’ worth of 8-bar guitar loops that need arrangements to call a home and I had a fun time bringing some field recordings of indigenous chants and my gamelan percussion fiddlings over to a local session with <a href="https://soundcloud.com/hexani">hex_</a> earlier this month. <em>I need to finish things!</em></p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/5NsV5awvlAnMcz01zJWPnQ?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Heavyheart</em>—munro</h3>
<p>Leave it to genre-bending Internet music provacateur in chief <a href="https://x.com/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt</a> to run with <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1831481465290551337">the meme</a> until it gets far enough out of hand to yield an exquisitely curated <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/78fb8mCjI4ZFk50yeiqYNM?si=s0o_XCk5QqCa01sgWprj8Q">27-song compilation release</a> from Tabula Rasa with a <a href="https://www.tabularasarecords.net/collections/hit-em">complementary merch drop.</a> munro’s track was the stickiest in my rotation, but the gamut covered by the other contributors showcases some really exciting production. 212 BPM. 5/4 time. Super crunched out sounds. Thank you to Drew for the tweet that started it all, and of course Thank You Dream Girl.</p>
<div class="mt-100 flex-center"><div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">had a dream I was at a rave talking to a girl and she told me about a genre called “hit em” that is in 5/4 time at 212 bpm with super crunched out sounds thank you dream girl</p>&mdash; DREW DANIEL (@DDDrewDaniel) <a href="https://twitter.com/DDDrewDaniel/status/1817910903557570569?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 29, 2024</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

</div></div>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7e7nlauAQ7866PPFMuxtgx?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>HEAL</em>—Machinedrum, AKTHESAVIOR, Deniro Farrar</h3>
<p>Machinedrum’s curatorial efforts on the compilation mentioned above came fresh off the heels of a deluxe LP release. <em>3FOR82_D3LUX3</em> brings even more solid cuts to the table than the original release from back in the spring and this track found me again at the right time in life to embed itself deeply in my rotation. It’s been over 10 years since the <em>Vapor City</em> era and somehow this guy is still finding new things to execute very well. I enjoy the range of experimentation in his crossovers into black music. Not everything hits for me—e.g. I don’t <em>dislike</em> the Jesse Boykins III collaborations, but it’s easy to find R&amp;B I’m more fond of. <em>Kane Train</em> with Freddy Gibbs (2020) was a smash by comparison; a definitive step up in Machinedrum’s ability to find a pocket in hip-hop production with vocal features. <em>HEAL</em> (2024) takes that deeper than production and performance into the realm of transcendent emotional appeal. It’s perhaps a tad less instrumentally inventive but still exquisitely arranged, sitting behind the vocal where it needs to yet still placing melodic variation and dynamic highs where they fit best. Stellar and moving vocal performance and message: life is hard… find a way to push through.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Vz1AtKebBGUyQm6O77Yan?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Lullaby</em>—TURQUOISEDEATH</h3>
<p>I’ve been riding around at night a lot with TURQUOISEDEATH. I’d comfortably put <em>Kaleidoscope</em> in the 2024 sleepers category; definitely unexpected replay value. Solid balance of ethereal ambiance, danceable tempos, and pedal to the metal breakbeat-filled DnB/jungle-esque goodness—not terribly novel, but thoroughly enjoyable.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1NKyiSyZyvz6mHgB4KSKbb?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>
<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Jan+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>