<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-02-11T17:59:12-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Stedman Halliday</title><subtitle>Stedman Halliday is a technical generalist based in San Francisco creating values-aligned products, brands, media, and experiences.</subtitle><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><entry><title type="html">Selected Quotes: Feb 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Selected Quotes: Feb 2025" /><published>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-02-03T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/02/03/selected-quotes"><![CDATA[<h2 id="hermann-hesse-on-not-reading">Hermann Hesse on <em>not</em> reading</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Stand just once at the stage where the stone by the road means as much to you as Goethe and Tolstoy, you will thereafter gain from Goethe, Tolstoy, and all poets infinitely more value, more sap and honey, more affirmation of life and of yourself than ever before.</em></p>

  <p><em>For the works of Goethe are not Goethe and the volumes of Dostoevsky are not Dostoevsky, they are only an attempt, a dubious and never successful attempt, to conjure up the many-voiced multitudinous world of which he was the central point.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Hermann Hesse, <em>On Reading Books</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="thomas-merton-on-the-yips">Thomas Merton on the yips</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>When an archer is shooting for nothing he has all his skill. If he shoots for a brass buckle he is already nervous. If he shoots for a prize of gold he goes blind or sees two targets—he is out of his mind. His skill has not changed, but the prize divides him. He cares, he thinks more of winning than of shooting—and the need to win drains him of power.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Thomas Merton, <em>The Way of Chuang Tzu</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="seneca-the-younger-on-true-friendship">Seneca the Younger on true friendship</h2>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>One who seeks friendship for favorable occasions strips it of all its nobility.</em></p>

  <p><em>If you consider any man a friend whom you do not trust as you trust yourself, you are mightily mistaken and you do not sufficiently understand what true friendship means… When friendship is settled, you must trust; before friendship is formed, you must pass judgment. Those persons indeed put last first and confound their duties, who… judge a man after they have made him their friend, instead of making him their friend after they have judged him. Ponder for a long time whether you shall admit a given person to your friendship; but when you have decided to admit him, welcome him with all your heart and soul. Speak as boldly with him as with yourself… Regard him as loyal and you will make him loyal.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Seneca the Younger</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Selected+Quotes%3A+Feb+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what resonated with you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="quotes" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*Selected Quotes* periodically presents thoughtfully curated quotes to inspire reflection on whatever resonates.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">7 Songs: Jan 2025</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="7 Songs: Jan 2025" /><published>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2025/01/31/7-songs"><![CDATA[<h3><em>Stone Woman Gives Birth To A Child At Night</em>—Mount Eerie</h3>
<p>I’ve spent much of autumn’s turn to winter coasting around California in a sedan. I’m surprised at how long it’s taken me to give the roads their fair due with amount of time I’ve lived in California while owning a car. When Mount Eerie’s been on, I’ve found myself stopping more frequently to contemplate whatever’s knocking at the threshold of my attention—a scenic vista or a mundane slice of time. Awareness has taken on a wide range of flavors from slow and viscous to bold, sweeping, and dynamic. It’s an appropriate soundtrack for being present nowhere in particular.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2xeAZhRIegjVgPyd6Hr4x7?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Circles</em>—Thrice</h3>
<p>There’s something I truly appreciate about the way many gems from Thrice’s wide-ranging discography allow themselves <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1879417785857761549">to be found</a> and sat within time and again. <em>Beggars</em> is one of my favorite records and <em>Circles</em> is a highlight that’s equal parts somber and expansive, with a small measure of twinkling hope. The lyrics characterize humans as intrepid yet futile in our perennial quests to cast ourselves into the dark and build upon what we know despite our ultimate ignorance, blindness, and fallibility. I haven’t watched these guys play in over 10 years (since the last dates of their farewell tour pre-reunion); perhaps it’s time to indulge a little nostalgia.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/3VppAi6bcWZo9y2Gc0VmPg?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hey Listen</em>—Drug Church</h3>
<p>Drug Church’s <em>Prude</em> was one of my favorite releases of 2024. It doesn’t break much new ground sonically, but the songs are well written despite their structural and lyrical simplicity. The tracklist is built with vignettes—often crushing ones—of life on the other side of cracks in modern life that many people would rather just pretend aren’t there (along with the people who’ve fallen through them). Hearing <em>Hey Listen</em> reminds me of an unlucky kid I used to get into trouble with when I was running low on luck myself. It makes me feel abruptly anxious and awfully guilty; sapped and resigned to abject cowardice, shame, and disappointment, yet ultimately grateful. It is indeed tough to find an upside, but there’s no hope for luck without the intent to search. Thanks to <a href="https://x.com/em32label/status/1885020104917954783">Carlos Jarquin</a> for listening to me yap about sad shit. <a href="https://forms.gle/Dt7X7wBvobb9cPdC7">Go tell him</a> about a song that means something to you.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1lwgbuHay1ujrTepc28fck?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Hollywood</em>—Toro y Moi, Benjamin Gibbard</h3>
<p>The end of last year saw me falling back into old patterns of landing myself in some total bullshit in Hollywood. Changing—truly and permanently changing—is a tall order. I guess I’m working my way up to it, but it’s really nobody’s business to even try to help me with this stuff anymore. On an entirely separate note, instrumental production is resonating with me here as creative inspiration. I’m sitting on several years’ worth of 8-bar guitar loops that need arrangements to call a home and I had a fun time bringing some field recordings of indigenous chants and my gamelan percussion fiddlings over to a local session with <a href="https://soundcloud.com/hexani">hex_</a> earlier this month. <em>I need to finish things!</em></p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/5NsV5awvlAnMcz01zJWPnQ?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Heavyheart</em>—munro</h3>
<p>Leave it to genre-bending Internet music provacateur in chief <a href="https://x.com/yungskrrt">Yung Skrrt</a> to run with <a href="https://x.com/stedmanhalliday/status/1831481465290551337">the meme</a> until it gets far enough out of hand to yield an exquisitely curated <a href="https://open.spotify.com/album/78fb8mCjI4ZFk50yeiqYNM?si=s0o_XCk5QqCa01sgWprj8Q">27-song compilation release</a> from Tabula Rasa with a <a href="https://www.tabularasarecords.net/collections/hit-em">complementary merch drop.</a> munro’s track was the stickiest in my rotation, but the gamut covered by the other contributors showcases some really exciting production. 212 BPM. 5/4 time. Super crunched out sounds. Thank you to Drew for the tweet that started it all, and of course Thank You Dream Girl.</p>
<div class="mt-100 flex-center"><div class="jekyll-twitter-plugin"><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">had a dream I was at a rave talking to a girl and she told me about a genre called “hit em” that is in 5/4 time at 212 bpm with super crunched out sounds thank you dream girl</p>&mdash; DREW DANIEL (@DDDrewDaniel) <a href="https://twitter.com/DDDrewDaniel/status/1817910903557570569?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 29, 2024</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

</div></div>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/7e7nlauAQ7866PPFMuxtgx?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>HEAL</em>—Machinedrum, AKTHESAVIOR, Deniro Farrar</h3>
<p>Machinedrum’s curatorial efforts on the compilation mentioned above came fresh off the heels of a deluxe LP release. <em>3FOR82_D3LUX3</em> brings even more solid cuts to the table than the original release from back in the spring and this track found me again at the right time in life to embed itself deeply in my rotation. It’s been over 10 years since the <em>Vapor City</em> era and somehow this guy is still finding new things to execute very well. I enjoy the range of experimentation in his crossovers into black music. Not everything hits for me—e.g. I don’t <em>dislike</em> the Jesse Boykins III collaborations, but it’s easy to find R&amp;B I’m more fond of. <em>Kane Train</em> with Freddy Gibbs (2020) was a smash by comparison; a definitive step up in Machinedrum’s ability to find a pocket in hip-hop production with vocal features. <em>HEAL</em> (2024) takes that deeper than production and performance into the realm of transcendent emotional appeal. It’s perhaps a tad less instrumentally inventive but still exquisitely arranged, sitting behind the vocal where it needs to yet still placing melodic variation and dynamic highs where they fit best. Stellar and moving vocal performance and message: life is hard… find a way to push through.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1Vz1AtKebBGUyQm6O77Yan?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<h3 class="mt-200"><em>Lullaby</em>—TURQUOISEDEATH</h3>
<p>I’ve been riding around at night a lot with TURQUOISEDEATH. I’d comfortably put <em>Kaleidoscope</em> in the 2024 sleepers category; definitely unexpected replay value. Solid balance of ethereal ambiance, danceable tempos, and pedal to the metal breakbeat-filled DnB/jungle-esque goodness—not terribly novel, but thoroughly enjoyable.</p>
<iframe class="mt-50" style="border-radius:12px" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/1NKyiSyZyvz6mHgB4KSKbb?utm_source=generator" width="100%" height="152" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen="" allow="autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; fullscreen; picture-in-picture" loading="lazy"></iframe>

<div class="soft-break"></div>
<p>If you’ve read this far (thanks), you probably like music quite a lot. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+7+Songs%3A+Jan+2025.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to get some <code>🏓 Playlist Ping Pong</code> going or chat about music.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="music" /><category term="7 songs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[*7 Songs* periodically features curated tracks and commentary for a more personal music discovery experience.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /><published>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-09-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/circadian-propranolol"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" alt="Circadian Rhythm Alteration with Propranolol" /></p>

<p class="mt-200">Ever wished you could hack your sleep schedule, beat jetlag, or stay sharp through an all-nighter without feeling like a zombie? Enter propranolol—a seemingly ordinary beta blocker with some extraordinary tricks up its sleeve. From calming anxiety to resetting your internal clock, propranolol might just be the secret weapon you've been looking for to take control of your sleep and energy levels.</p>

<div class="mv-200 divider-thin"></div>

<h2 id="overview-of-beta-blockers">Overview of beta blockers</h2>

<h3 id="mechanism-of-action">Mechanism of action</h3>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<p>Beta blockers generally inhibit signals from the sympathetic nervous system, leading to reduced anxiety levels by limiting the heart’s ability to respond to stress.</p>

<h3 id="beta-blocker-subtypes">Beta blocker subtypes</h3>

<p>Cardioselective beta blockers mainly work on the heart by blocking beta-1 receptors, which helps lower heart rate and blood pressure. Because they focus more on the heart, they don’t affect the lungs as much, making them safer for people with breathing problems like asthma or COPD.</p>

<p>Non-selective beta blockers block both beta-1 and beta-2 receptors. Since beta-2 receptors are found in the lungs, blood vessels, and muscles, these drugs can affect more than just the heart. This can cause side effects like tightening of the airways, making them less safe for people with asthma or COPD.</p>

<h3 id="applications-for-anxiety">Applications for Anxiety</h3>

<p>This mechanism is particularly beneficial for individuals with social anxiety or general anxiety disorders, as it mitigates physical symptoms of anxiety.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="propranolol-specifics">Propranolol specifics</h2>

<p>Propranolol is a non-selective beta blocker. It is the most lipophilic (fat-soluble) among them, which enables it to cross the blood-brain barrier more effectively.</p>

<h3 id="effects-on-circadian-rhythm">Effects on circadian rhythm</h3>

<p>When propranolol crosses into the brain, it affects the suprachiasmatic nucleus (SCN) in a way that mimics morning blue light exposure. This can lower the body’s natural production of melatonin, which might lead to insomnia and nightmares.</p>

<h3 id="application">Application</h3>

<p>Propranolol can be used to intentionally reduce melatonin production, making it easier to stay awake longer, such as when pulling an all-nighter. It can also be used to reset a chronically desynchronized sleep schedule or overcome jetlag.</p>

<h2 id="example-reversing-a-nocturnal-routine">Example: reversing a nocturnal routine</h2>

<h3 id="background">Background</h3>

<p>Drue Wetsel, a 25-year-old software engineer, has been stuck in a nocturnal routine, habitually falling asleep at 5 am and waking up around 1 pm. He wants to reset his sleep schedule to fall asleep at midnight and wake up at 8 am to align better with a more typical workday and improve his overall health.</p>

<h3 id="circadian-reset-protocol">Circadian reset protocol</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>5 am:</strong> Drue goes to bed at his usual time and sets an alarm for 8 am, planning to get only 3 hours of sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>8 am:</strong> He wakes up, takes propranolol, and uses caffeine to power through the day on minimal sleep.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 pm – 6 pm:</strong> Drue keeps himself busy and alert, using a brief NSDR (non-sleep deep rest) session to avoid napping and maintain energy.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>12 am:</strong> Exhausted, Drue finally goes to bed at his new target bedtime, setting an alarm for 8 am to reinforce the new schedule.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Following days:</strong> Drue sticks to the midnight-to-8 am sleep schedule, using propranolol and mild stimulants as needed, until it becomes his new norm.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="additional-medical-applications">Additional medical applications</h2>

<p><strong>Thyroid storm management:</strong> Propranolol helps manage dangerously fast heart rate and high blood pressure caused by excessive thyroid hormone by slowing down the heart and easing other symptoms like anxiety and tremors.</p>

<p><strong>Prevention of cardiac remodeling:</strong> propranolol can help prevent changes in heart structure caused by heart failure (however, other beta blockers are more commonly used for this purpose).</p>

<p><strong>Prophylactic use in cirrhotics:</strong> variceal bleeding occurs when swollen veins in the esophagus or stomach burst and bleed due to liver disease. Non-selective beta blockers like propranolol help prevent this by reducing pressure in those veins.</p>

<p><strong>Treatment of essential tremors:</strong> essential tremors cause uncontrollable shaking, often in the hands. Propranolol helps reduce this shaking, making it easier for people to do everyday tasks.</p>

<h2 id="cautions-and-side-effects">Cautions and side effects</h2>

<p><strong>Respiratory concerns:</strong> propranolol and other non-selective beta blockers can exacerbate asthma and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD).</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>

<p>In conclusion, propranolol is a versatile non-selective beta blocker with a range of applications, from managing anxiety and essential tremors to preventing serious complications in conditions like thyroid storm and cirrhosis. Its ability to cross the blood-brain barrier makes it particularly effective for altering circadian rhythms, offering a solution for those needing to reset their sleep schedules. However, caution is necessary, especially for individuals with respiratory conditions, as propranolol can exacerbate issues like asthma and COPD. Consult a healthcare professional for guidance before using propranolol.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p><a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Circadian+Rhythm+Alteration+with+Propranolol.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you enjoyed this post or if you’ve got any corrections I should know about. Special thanks to <a href="https://substack.com/@quixoteknight">quixoteknight</a> for enriching this post with invaluable insights into medical pharmacology. Read what they have to say about melatonin next.</p>

<h2 class="mt-200 text-center">Related content</h2>
<div class="substack-post-embed" style="margin: 0 auto; border-radius: 12px; overflow: hidden"><p lang="en">Melatonin: MMTYWTK Addendum by QK</p><p>Fun Practical Applications of Abusing Endogenous Neurohormones</p><a data-post-link="" href="https://optimizeeverything.substack.com/p/melatonin-mmtywtk-addendum">Read on Substack</a></div>
<script async="" src="https://substack.com/embedjs/embed.js" charset="utf-8"></script>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday and [quixoteknight](https://substack.com/@quixoteknight)</name></author><category term="health" /><category term="drugs" /><category term="sleep" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reset your sleep clock or beat jetlag with beta blockers]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/img/2024-09-04-circadian-propranolol-00.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’ve Learned from Mentorship</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/08/27/what-i-ve-learned-from-mentorship" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I’ve Learned from Mentorship" /><published>2018-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2018-08-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/08/27/what-i-ve-learned-from-mentorship</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/08/27/what-i-ve-learned-from-mentorship"><![CDATA[<figure>
<img alt="Sister Corita Kent" src="/assets/img/2018-08-27-corita-kent.webp" />
<figcaption>Corita Kent, also known as Sister Mary Corita, was an artist with an innovative approach to design and education. (Source: <a href="https://www.corita.org/">Corita.org</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><em>Cool news: I’ve been working with the leadership team at Designers Guild to launch an online mentorship program this September. Designers Guild is a community of 10,000+ designers committed to discussing, learning, and growing together. The outpouring of interest in our upcoming program (over 400 pupils and 100 mentors have applied) encouraged us to open up a dialogue about mentorship expectations and experiences. Here are some of my stories.</em></p>

<h2 id="my-first-mentor">My first mentor</h2>

<p>My first mentorship experience began after I started contracting freelance design work in high school. (This was the start of my design career around eight or nine years ago.) After a couple years of independently learning how to design and code, a friend’s dad commissioned me to produce a website for his legal firm. I was around 15 years old and it was my first freelance gig. It went well and I quickly landed another project via referral, this one with a senior designer on it.</p>

<p>This designer—who became my first mentor—was in his 50s with a lot of more traditional agency experience. Our communication styles meshed well and we got along instantly. My skillset complemented his experience well. He would handle the clients, lead design direction, manage projects, and present work. I filled in the gaps with my knowledge of technology and new media. We’ve worked together on a lot of projects since.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>I learned about the administrative and hustling aspects of freelance work; my communication skills with clients and collaborators flourished.</li>
  <li>I gained a ton of confidence and experience through immersion.</li>
  <li>I began a long relationship with someone who remains an important part of my professional support network.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>There was a generational gap between our hard skillsets.</li>
  <li>I didn’t frequently get opportunities to push the limits of my skills or creative sensibilities.</li>
  <li>Some of the work and clients became less appealing over the years as my interests matured; I sought more opportunities for growth.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="my-second-mentor">My second mentor</h2>

<p>It was the summer after my first year of design school and I’d been working alongside my first mentor for a couple years. It surprised me to learn that his wife was a renowned food photographer. He got me a second job managing her studio while I worked a design internship. Despite not being a designer, she became my second mentor. I learned far more from her than at my internship that summer.</p>

<p>My old mentor left agency life behind for a more flexible freelance routine, but his wife was the hardest hustler I had ever met. Alongside shooting, she ran a brick-and-mortar studio that doubled as an event space. She had a lot more administrative overhead to manage. She set the bar high for me and pushed me very hard, but never failed to praise and reward me when I met her expectations.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>I learned a ton about entrepreneurship and the day-to-day details of running a business (versus freelancing).</li>
  <li>Managing and facilitating larger on-site productions became second nature. Necessity forced me to learn many things quickly.</li>
  <li>I began to understand that I liked providing value more than making things. I felt most rewarded when my skills worked in tandem to maximize the value I could provide.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>My hard skills and career trajectory were even more misaligned than they were with my previous mentor.</li>
  <li>Working two jobs led to my first experience with burnout the following semester.</li>
  <li>I possessed neither the foresight nor soft skills to make lasting connections in a parallel creative industry.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="my-last-mentor">My last mentor</h2>

<p>My last mentor was assigned to me in design school. In hindsight, I didn’t have the social/emotional maturity to take full advantage of that relationship. The fact that school was a more pressurized environment exacerbated this. I loved my mentor’s energy as a person, but her communication style wasn’t compatible with mine. I felt that she was rather abstract and indirect at times. Even though I studied graphic design in a program of my choice, the perfect mentor was elusive. Finding someone with a matching philosophy, skillset, and communication style was difficult. Prompted by our skillset incongruence, my mentor instructed me to seek other advisors. This became an obstacle to transparency, resulting in negative feedback on important work.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>

<ul>
  <li>She bolstered my focus on ethics. She once said she’d eat canned soup every night if it meant she got to do the work that made her proud.</li>
  <li>She never stopped encouraging me to write.</li>
  <li>I grew after-the-fact by learning from my failures.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li>Our communication styles were incompatible.</li>
  <li>Our philosophies, skills, and career trajectories were somewhat mismatched.</li>
  <li>The pressurized environment and academic consequences led to a decline in my confidence.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="key-takeaways-from-my-mentorship-experiences">Key takeaways from my mentorship experiences</h2>

<ul>
  <li><strong>One of the most crucial aspects of a mentor-pupil relationship is communicative compatibility.</strong> Ideas don’t mean anything (or may even become harmful) when lost in translation.</li>
  <li><strong>Experience is the best teacher.</strong> Sometimes, it’s quite important that a mentor has walked the (approximate) path that a pupil would like to take in their career.</li>
  <li>Despite a mismatch in hard skills or career trajectory, a pupil can still learn a lot from a mentor. <strong>Sometimes what complements a pupil’s hard skills and fills in the gaps can be just as—if not more—important to their long-term success.</strong></li>
  <li>A good mentor will challenge pupils, hold them accountable, and examine failures to create teachable moments, but will also <strong>remember to reward and praise pupils, emphasizing their strengths.</strong></li>
  <li>Good mentors usually ask a lot of questions before giving advice. <strong>Inquiry before judgment is a strong general principle for teachers.</strong></li>
  <li><strong>Pupils are responsible for pulling the best out of their mentors</strong>—not just the other way around. Pupils must be proactive and learn to actively solicit mentor input to meet their unique needs.</li>
</ul>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>My most recent relationship with a mentor was my most difficult, but I may have grown the most from it. I learned how to be more proactive and ask for what I need. I realized how important a good cultural and environmental fit is to the success of individuals and institutions. I learned about my limitations and what I could do to address them.</p>

<p>Overall, my experiences have left me with a desire for a mentor whose philosophy, experience, and goals more closely match my interests. I’m at a point in my career where I know a bit more about what I want than I did in design school. Failing that, at least I know which questions I’ve got to ask to find the right answers. Finding a strong fit and learning from community feedback are what I’m most excited about when it comes to starting a new mentorship program.</p>

<p>I’d like to conclude this story with some wisdom from Sister Corita Kent: a notable educator in the arts. Below are her famous rules for the Immaculate Heart College Art Department. Many of them apply to relationships between mentors and pupils.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="Sister Corita Kent's ten rules" src="/assets/img/2018-08-27-ten-rules.webp" />
</figure>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>RULE 1: Find a place you trust, and then try trusting it for awhile.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 2: General duties of a student — pull everything out of your teacher; pull everything out of your fellow students.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 3: General duties of a teacher — pull everything out of your students.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 4: Consider everything an experiment.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 5: Be self-disciplined — this means finding someone wise or smart and choosing to follow them. To be disciplined is to follow in a good way. To be self-disciplined is to follow in a better way.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 6: Nothing is a mistake. There’s no win and no fail, there’s only make.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 7: The only rule is work. If you work it will lead to something. It’s the people who do all of the work all of the time who eventually catch on to things.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 8: Don’t try to create and analyze at the same time. They’re different processes.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 9: Be happy whenever you can manage it. Enjoy yourself. It’s lighter than you think.</em></p>

  <p><em>RULE 10: “We’re breaking all the rules. Even our own rules. And how do we do that? By leaving plenty of room for X quantities.” (John Cage)</em></p>

  <p><em>HELPFUL HINTS: Always be around. Come or go to everything. Always go to classes. Read anything you can get your hands on. Look at movies carefully, often. Save everything — it might come in handy later.</em></p>

  <p><em>There should be new rules next week.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you like this post? Do you have any thoughts about or experiences with mentorship that you’d like to share? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+What+I%E2%80%99ve+Learned+from+Mentorship.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="design" /><category term="work" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Reflecting on my experiences with mentorship]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Q&amp;amp;A: How can digital designers mix RGB colors more effectively?</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/02/05/rgb-color-mixing.md" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Q&amp;amp;A: How can digital designers mix RGB colors more effectively?" /><published>2018-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2018-02-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/02/05/rgb-color-mixing.md</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2018/02/05/rgb-color-mixing.md"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-spectrum.webp" alt="" /></p>

<p class="mt-200"><em>Q&amp;A is a column in which I’ll post long-form answers to thought-provoking questions. This particular question was inspired by a thread in [Designers Guild](https://facebook.com/groups/designguild), a Facebook community that I moderate. Designers Guild consists of 10,000+ designers committed to discussing, learning, and growing together.</em></p>

<h2 class="mt-200">The question</h2>

<p><em>Recently, pixel artist and game designer <a href="https://twitter.com/rayslynyrd">Slynyrd</a> published a great <a href="http://www.slynyrd.com/blog/2018/1/10/pixelblog-1-color-palettes">blog post</a> walking readers through a process for creating awesome pixel art color palettes. The tutorial focuses on selecting colors by manipulating HSB properties (hue, saturation, and brightness). This prompted a question about designers’ favorite ways to mix color.</em></p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="the-answer">The answer</h2>

<p>I’ve always found generating HSB swatches to be the most intuitive method for novice designers to make color selections. Generating a single swatch with the HSB scales feels the most analogous to picking out a swatch from a color book in real life: you basically choose the general color you want (hue) then filter down to find your swatch by selecting for finer attributes of that general color (saturation and brightness). These three properties of a color are what give the scale its name (HSB = hue, saturation, brightness).</p>

<p>However, over the last couple years, I’ve taken a liking to directly mixing RGB in many situations (especially when it comes to building out larger palettes). Instead of picking swatches from a color book, it’s more analogous to mixing paint in a palette (except that mixing in RGB is additive rather than subtractive, so it’s technically mixing light; more on this later). RGB is named for the three channels of light mixed to produce an onscreen color (RGB = red, green, blue).</p>

<p><strong>Like a swatch book, HSB provides a great scale for <em>finding</em> a color.</strong> It can be useful for pinning down a match for the color you’ve seen in your head, on a screen, or in the real world. <strong>Like a painter’s palette, RGB provides a great space for <em>mixing</em> color.</strong> It can be used to create organic and harmonious relationships between two or more colors in a palette.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="color mixing" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-mixing.webp" />
<figcaption>While HSB can be like a swatch book for finding colors, RGB can be like a palette for mixing them.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="the-main-idea">The main idea</h3>

<p>To start mixing in RGB, think of each channel as a bucket of red, green, or blue paint. With 8 bits per channel, you have 256 levels of granularity for how much of that color you want to mix in; 255 is the whole bucket, 192 = three quarters, 128 = half bucket, 64 = quarter bucket, and so on. Once in the ballpark, you can adjust the mix by finer increments (e.g. 4 = 1/64 bucket).</p>

<figure>
<img alt="red channel" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-red-channel.webp" />
<figcaption>Removing color from the red channel results in darker, less saturated reds. At 64, the channels is 1/4 full.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>What I like about this method:</strong> preserving the channel ratios across colors and finding ways to recombine and riff on them can create more natural color harmonies amongst all of the swatches that end up in my palette. There’s something poetic about building color palettes by using the parameters of the color space itself as mixing model. When I finally got comfortable with this method, it felt a little like when I first understood how to utilize the grid for layouts; you’re not just picking a set of colors that look good, you’re outlining a system that encourages discretionary relationships in order to arrive at it.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="channel mixing" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-channel-mixing.webp" />
<figcaption>Channel ratios: the cerulean and yellow swatches above both have equal amounts of green (3/4 channel) mixed into another full channel (either blue or red).</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>By simply swapping a full blue channel for a red one, we’ve arrived at a yellow that complements the cerulean quite nicely.</p>

<h3 id="comparison-with-hsb">Comparison with HSB</h3>

<p>Comparatively, the same result can be attained in HSB by shifting the hue +210º (7/12) or -150º (-5/12). This exercise can often get a little more arbitrary for two main reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Different hues are affected unequally by brightness and saturation shifts as a result of varying <em>natural</em> value and chroma (for example, at a given saturation and brightness we still perceive a yellow hue as brighter than a violet one). The perceptual distance between a pure hue and white for example can also vary depending on which hue you’re working with.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Spatially mapping the distance from red to magenta onto the 360º of a circle can make for a less-than-intuitive visualization of hues. If color stops were placed in regular intervals along this scale, some shifts in hue might appear greater than others even though the stops are equidistant. This is also a result of the varying natural value and chroma of each hue. The best way to visually estimate which degrees correspond to which hues in HSB is with the old mnemonic from science class for the colors of the visible light spectrum: <em>Roy G. Biv</em> (red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, violet). Notice that this doesn’t map too cleanly onto the color wheel in even increments (blue and indigo are off the mark).</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<figure>
<img alt="color wheel" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-color-wheel.webp" />
<figcaption>Visualizing hue in degrees is difficult. Using ~51.5º increments, blue and indigo are off the mark!</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>All that being said, mixing in HSB isn’t bad at all. Here’s a good <a href="https://learnui.design/blog/the-hsb-color-system-practicioners-primer.html">primer</a> on it. The rest of this answer will focus on the strengths of an RGB mixing process.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h3 id="additive-vs-subtractive-color">Additive vs. Subtractive Color</h3>

<p>Something mentioned earlier was that RGB is <em>additive</em> rather than <em>subtractive</em>. What <em>additive</em> means is that adding more color information from any channel adds light to make brighter colors, ultimately resulting in white. You can see the summation of colors resulting in white in the color wheel graphic above as well as the diagram below. Compare this to <em>subtractive</em> mixing, where more color information subtracts light to make darker colors (ultimately black).</p>

<figure>
<img alt="additive and subtractive color" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-additive=subtractive.webp" />
<figcaption>Additive color adds light to make white. Subtractive color subtracts light to make black.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="example-cool-gradient">Example: Cool Gradient</h3>

<p>Here’s an example of how I like to mix colors in RGB. We’ll begin a palette by making swatches to create this cool gradient:</p>

<figure>
<img src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-cool-gradient.webp" />
</figure>

<h4 id="starting-with-blue">Starting with blue</h4>

<p>1. We know we want to start with a blue, so let’s just flood the blue channel all the way; <strong>RGB(0,0,255).</strong></p>

<figure>
<img alt="full blue channel" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-swatch.webp" />
<figcaption>Flooding the blue channel all the way gets us a deep blue.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>2. Good start, but it’s too dark and just too blue.</p>

<ul>
  <li>We’d like a lighter color—remember that since RGB is additive, we can get that by adding color information to another channel.</li>
  <li>We’re going to be matching it with a greener hue, so it makes sense that the channel we add should be green.</li>
  <li>Looking back at the additive color diagram, mixing a full blue channel with a full green channel results in cyan. We want a lighter blue but not <em>that</em> light.</li>
  <li>We can add green in small amounts like mixing paint in to find a sweet spot. What if we split our channel (256 levels) into eighths (256/8 = 32)? That way, every time we add 32 levels to the green channel, it’s like moving 1/8 of the way from full blue to cyan.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="blue channel levels" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-swatches.webp" />
<figcaption>Adding 32 (1/8) green each time gradually creates a lighter blue (moving towards cyan).</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>That last iteration looks pretty good; blue, but not too dark and not too saturated. We also have a really clean ratio between channels: <strong>RGB(0,96,255) = 0:3:8 RGB ratio.</strong></p>

<h4 id="from-blue-to-green">From blue to green</h4>

<p>Now that we have a nice blue swatch, let’s get another concordant swatch going. Looking at our intended result, we want this one to be greener and a good bit brighter.</p>

<p>1. Let’s take care of <em>greener</em> first.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Remember that our first color was predominantly blue, but had a little green added to move it towards cyan.</li>
  <li>Swapping the values for the G and B channels will get us a color that is equidistant from cyan, but predominantly green instead of blue.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="blue and green channels" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-green-swatches.webp" />
<figcaption>Swapping the values of the blue and green channels gives us an analogous green swatch.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>2. Lookin’ alright! These swatches already feel quite analogous in terms of brightness and saturation because they share similar channel ratios.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Both swatches are equidistant from white in the color space since the total amount color in both swatches is equivalent. Both have 351 levels (96 + 255), but they’re just distributed inversely across the blue and green channels.</li>
  <li>The analogous nature of the colors is enforced by our logical use of the additive color chart. Essentially, the result of inverting the channel values was to reflect our original color across the cyan axis of the chart.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="color reflection diagram" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-additive-diagram.webp" />
<figcaption>Reflection across the cyan axis; both colors are equidistant from white.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>3. We’re off to a good start, but looking back at our intended result, we want a cooler palette that might call for a bluer green with a lighter touch; something closer to cyan but not quite.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="blue and green mixing" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-green-mixing.webp" />
<figcaption>Our intended result lies in the direction of cyan; we want to add color to the blue channel.</figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
  <li>We know that adding blue will get us there, but how much blue do we need? This is a good time to revisit the channel ratios.</li>
  <li><strong>RGB(0,255,96) = 0:8:3 RGB ratio…</strong> what if we just mixed in double the amount of blue? This would get us a 0:8:6 ratio — not all the way to cyan but enough to cool our green down.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="aquamarine" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-aquamarine.webp" />
<figcaption>The sweet spot: a nice, strong aquamarine with a 0:8:6 RGB ratio.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Looks like the sweet spot: a nice, strong aquamarine with a 0:8:6 RGB ratio. The ratio keeps our channels in 8 parts and plays really nicely with our other color’s 0:3:8 ratio.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="blue to blue-green gradient" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-green-gradient.webp" />
<figcaption>We’ve now mixed both the swatches necessary for our original cool gradient.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>From this point, we can shuffle the ratios even more to discover additional harmonious swatches inside the spectrum we’ve just established. We can make more minute adjustments using the same logic of splitting the channel levels into smaller fractions. We can bring in some of the starting blues from before for dark swatches, or even start incorporating the red channel into our existing ratios to get more contrasting colors. There are a lot of places to go, but hopefully, this example illustrates the thinking behind building more organic color relationships in the RGB color space.</p>

<figure>
<img src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-cool-gradient.webp" />
</figure>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h3 id="how-to-see-hexadecimal-colors-in-your-head">How to see hexadecimal colors in your head</h3>

<p><em>I made a 2-minute YouTube tutorial for a neat trick to visualize hexadecimal triplets that abridges some information found in the rest of the article. You can use this method as a practical shortcut in your work or as a cool party trick.</em></p>

<figure>
<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style><div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/3-9k_nrGdhY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
</figure>

<h3 id="hexadecimal-colors">Hexadecimal colors</h3>

<p>An additional bonus of mixing directly in the RGB color space is that we can garner a more intuitive understanding of its hexadecimal representations. Because a color’s hexadecimal representation (e.g. #0060FF) maps to its RGB values, mixing in RGB can gradually acquaint us more with these hex codes up to the point where we’re even mixing colors directly in hex. Here’s how to convert a hexadecimal color to its decimal RGB values:</p>

<p>1. Split your hex number into 3 groups of 2 characters.</p>

<ul>
  <li>e.g. #0060FF = 00 | 60 | FF</li>
  <li>Each group now represents the R, G, or B channel respectively</li>
</ul>

<p>2. Keep in mind that even the letters here are <em>digits</em>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>00 in the red channel means 0 red… simple enough</li>
  <li>But FF = 255? <em>What?</em></li>
  <li>We’re used to digits in a <em>decimal</em> system. <em>Dec</em> = 10; 10 digits (0–9).</li>
  <li><em>Hex</em> = 6 and <em>dec</em> = 10; <em>hexadecimal</em> uses 16 digits (0–F).</li>
  <li>We already know how to count from 0–9, but in hexadecimal, we just keep counting with letters (A = 10, B = 11, …, F = 15). Just imagine the letters as a single-digit representation of what would ordinarily be a number from 10–15 in our common decimal system.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="decimal to hexadecimal digit conversion" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-decimal-hexadecimal.webp" />
<figcaption>The sixteen hexadecimal digits (0–F) represent decimal values from 0–15.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>3. To convert your hex number to the decimal value for the channel:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Take the digit in the “tens” place (really the “sixteens” place in hex) and multiply it by 16 (or 16¹).</li>
  <li>Then take the digit in the “ones” place [and multiply it by 1 (or 16⁰)].</li>
  <li>Add the two together to get your decimal value.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="conversion-example">Conversion example</h4>

<p>Converting #0060FF to RGB:</p>

<figure>
<img alt="hexadecimal to decimal RGB conversion" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-hex-conversion.webp" />
<figcaption>Conversion table for hexadecimal to decimal RGB</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>#0060FF = RGB(0,96,255)</strong></p>

<p>You can reverse this process by dividing (Euclidean division) your decimal RGB value by 16. The quotient goes in the “tens” place of the hex number and the remainder goes in the “ones” place.</p>

<p>Converting RGB(0,96,255) to hexadecimal:</p>

<figure>
<img alt="decimal to hexadecimal RGB conversion" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-hex-conversion-01.webp" />
<figcaption>Conversion table for decimal to hexadecimal RGB</figcaption>
</figure>

<p><strong>RGB(0,96,255) = #0060FF</strong></p>

<h4 id="approximating-hexadecimal-channel-ratios">Approximating hexadecimal channel ratios</h4>

<p>The mental math for exact hex conversions can be slow and confusing at first. The best way to develop an intuition for how hexadecimal RGB works is just to approximate: you’ll get sharper and sharper with time until it’s second nature. Here’s an easy approximation scheme:</p>

<p>1. Split the hex string into 3 groups of 2 characters just like you would for a conversion to decimal.</p>

<p>2. Round each channel’s value to the nearest 0.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If the second digit is 8 or above, round up (e.g. 3A rounds to 40); you can round high Fs to a theoretical G0</li>
  <li>Otherwise round down (e.g. 37 rounds to 30)</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="hexadecimal rounding" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-decimal-hexadecimal-01.webp" />
<figcaption>Hexadecimal digits 8–F round up; 0–7 round down.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>3. You now have a rough ratio for your channel mix: the first digit tells you approximately how many <em>sixteenths</em> of that color you’ve added.</p>

<p>For example: <strong>#873AFF</strong> rounds to <strong>80 | 40 | G0</strong>. 8/16 red, 4/16 green, and 16/16 blue gives us an approximate <strong>2:1:4 RGB ratio</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>Remember when we added green by 1/8 increments to our first blue swatches? 1/8 = 2/16; you can clearly see us adding 2/16 of green each time the first digit in the green channel’s hex number increases by 2.</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="blue channel values" src="/assets/img/2018-02-05-blue-swatches-01.webp" />
<figcaption>Each time the first digit in the green channel’s hex number increases by 2, it’s like adding 2/16 of green.</figcaption>
</figure>

<ul>
  <li>You’re in good shape when you get to the point where you can look at <em>#0060FF</em> and quickly tell that it’s full blue with some green mixed in (a little less than half the channel).</li>
  <li>Using our estimation technique from above, we can quickly see 6/16 green and 16/16 blue which simplifies to “3 parts green, 8 parts blue.” At this point, you’re seeing hexadecimal RGB color like a painter sees a palette.</li>
</ul>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>So there you have it, a primer for getting started with mixing in RGB. To recap, some of the advantages of mixing in RGB are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The ability to create more organic color relationships using channel ratios</li>
  <li>The opportunity to arrive at color palettes using a system that encourages discretionary relationships (much like the grid does for layouts)</li>
  <li>The congruence of building color palettes using the parameters of the color space itself as mixing model</li>
  <li>Not having to worry about the sometimes arbitrary effects of saturation and brightness on different hues or the 360º of the color wheel</li>
  <li>The convenience of developing an understanding of working with hexadecimal RGB color</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Happy mixing!</em></p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Did you enjoy this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Q%26A%3A+How+can+digital+designers+mix+RGB+colors+more+effectively%3F.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know what you liked about it.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday for [Prototypr](https://blog.prototypr.io/)</name></author><category term="design" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Different mental models for understanding additive color mixing]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">My Motives for Service</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/12/01/motives-for-service" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Motives for Service" /><published>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-12-01T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/12/01/motives-for-service</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/12/01/motives-for-service"><![CDATA[<h2 id="stop-me-if-youve-heard-this-one-before">Stop me if you’ve heard this one before…</h2>

<p><strong><em>Design will save the world!</em></strong> It’s a sentiment that everybody and their mom has heard at this point. Kanye proudly <a href="http://grist.org/cities/kanye-west-says-design-can-save-the-world-students-respond/">proclaimed it</a>. David Carson <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/798568-graphic-design-will-save-the-world-right-after-rock-and">cheekily lampooned it</a>. Perhaps Mike Monteiro <a href="https://deardesignstudent.com/can-design-save-the-world-8d3c1cd0efe7">articulated it best</a> in a moment of critical realness aimed at this sentiment that so unabashedly represents the self-celebratory nature of design as an industry:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>…the world isn’t usually changed by special people. It’s changed by ordinary people… Yes, designers can change the world. But it’s because we have the same responsibility as every other ordinary person.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Mike Monteiro, <em>Can Design Change the World?</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve thought a lot about social and civic responsibility… a lot about what I may owe to my immediate community and the world at large for investing in me as I’ve grown into the person that I am today. Once upon a time, I wrote:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In my future as a designer, I will exercise my potential to call other members of a global community to action for a better tomorrow by creating engaging experiences and tools that enable others to do the same on a multiplied scale.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Ever since then, I’ve been striving as best I can to identify pathways which allow me to embody that mission in the work I like to do. The years since I penned that statement have been filled with a good deal of experimentation, some successes, many failures, and several valuable lessons and discoveries. My search to fulfill my mission in a way that’s meaningful to me has encouraged a desire to explore aggressively.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="on-exploring">On exploring</h2>

<blockquote class="bigquote">Go far and wide early on and cultivate the patience to focus and go deep later, when clearer vision emerges from an amalgam of diverse experiences.</blockquote>

<figure><img alt="Imperial Wharf Railway Station" src="/assets/img/2017-12-01-london_train.webp" /></figure>

<p>It was advice that I was at first hesitant to follow, but upon consideration it felt like a good fit for my personality. There’s a golden moment in an episode of <em>The Knowledge Project</em> podcast featuring Naval Ravikant where he refers to this idea as the important transition in his career from a phase of exploration to one of execution. The <a href="https://podcasts.apple.com/us/podcast/18-naval-ravikant-the-angel-philosopher/id990149481?i=1000381983198">entire episode</a> is filled to the brim with a lot of other sage advice. It helps that I’ve always been a person who enjoys pursuing many (sometimes disparate) endeavors. Here are the cliff notes of what I’ve tried since writing that statement which abstractly identifies my motives:</p>

<ul>
  <li>I declared a minor where I learned about digital fabrication, algorithmic music, and a myriad of other things that weren’t exactly design-related.</li>
  <li>I helped launch an educational technology company called Kadenze to make arts and technology education more accessible and affordable.</li>
  <li>I toured several studios and agencies in New York and California wondering if that life could ever work for me.</li>
  <li>I graduated from CalArts!</li>
  <li>I interviewed for a small number of design positions in California through recruiters who were interested in my work. The opportunities seemed good on paper, but none of them really panned out. I must admit that I was more motivated to pursue them by financial pressures than by passion; for the most part, their missions never quite felt as meaningful as the work I was doing before.</li>
  <li>I wanted to learn more about the intersection of entrepreneurship and design, so I spent some time consulting for a couple early-stage technology companies in Palo Alto.</li>
  <li>I traveled to Liverpool, England to attend my first business conference, and to Florence, Italy to meet an engineering team.</li>
  <li>I saw a lot of other interesting things in Europe. My visit to the Bauhaus Archive in Berlin was highly emotional.</li>
  <li>I worked on numerous side-projects including a resource aggregator for Google’s TensorFlow library, a web application for genetics researchers, and tour promotions, album artwork, and websites for various independent artists and musicians.</li>
  <li>I became a moderator for <a href="http://facebook.com/groups/designguild/">Designers Guild</a>, an online community of over 10,000 designers committed to learning and growing together.</li>
  <li>Most importantly: <strong>I helped people whenever possible. I learned that I genuinely just love supporting others. Helping people simultaneously makes me feel useful and feels like the best use of my time; ideal.</strong></li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="People Supporting People" src="/assets/img/2017-12-01-people_supporting_people.webp" />
<figcaption><a href="http://bijanberahimi.com/">Bijan Berahimi's</a> 2016 poster and staircase for the Facebook Analog Research Laboratory inspire me. "Support others always and see it come back in spades."</figcaption>
</figure>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="on-getting-lost">On getting lost</h2>

<blockquote class="bigquote mt-50">There's a thing that many people forget to expect when they take up the mantle of exploration: it's not difficult to get lost… and I was pretty out there.</blockquote>

<figure>
<img alt="Lost in Liverpool" src="/assets/img/2017-12-01-lost_liverpool.webp" />
<figcaption>Lost in Liverpool (June 2016)</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Reconciling lessons from all of my experiences and understanding how to unify them into a workable vision for my future was going to take substantive consideration. I have Jenny Earnest to thank for pointing me in the right direction when she gifted me a copy of the 2017 edition of <em>What Color is Your Parachute?</em>, a classic job-hunting best-seller by Richard N. Bolles. I particularly appreciated the book’s helpful suggestion to perform a “self-inventory” so that I might craft that vision with integrity on the basis of my most genuine self — merits, flaws, and all.</p>

<figure>
<img alt="Thank You for Sharing" src="/assets/img/2017-12-01-tyfs.webp" />
<figcaption>P.S. check out Jenny's stimulating newsletter! <a href="https://mailchi.mp/dcab620a5166/tyfs">Thank You for Sharing</a> is one of the best parts of my email week.</figcaption>
</figure>

<h3 id="listen-to-your-friends">Listen to your friends?</h3>

<p>A thousand scattered conversations with friends also punctuated that period of deep self-reflection. Some memories of those back-and-forths remain more salient than others. I remember one mathematician friend throwing quite the jab after one of my extended musings about technology’s potential to elicit social change on a gargantuan scale.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>What are you gonna do, give people better iPhones?</em> 🙄</p>
</blockquote>

<p>He was being a jerk… but more importantly, he was being a jerk with a fair point. For all my belief in the ideals of social responsibility, that incisive retort deftly forced me to recognize and admit that the comforts and promises of ergonomic office chairs and steady paychecks always came first. It proved to be ammunition for further reflection. <em>What am I really here to do?</em></p>

<h3 id="search-your-feelings">Search your feelings</h3>

<p>Building relationships and pursuing community-oriented work struck a nerve with me for some reason. Maybe it’s because of all the online communities that have shaped my evolution as a designer over the last decade. Helping and encouraging others in various more socially hands-on roles tended to return a distinctly powerful energy which I frequently felt was missing from my work. The self-inventory process began to accelerate as I started to readily identify similarly meaningful feelings which had arisen in previous work contexts.</p>

<p>One sentiment that stuck with me from my time in edtech was a festering disillusionment concerning how distant and removed I felt from the people I was helping. Many amazing, smart, and talented people benefitted from the reach of the work I was doing and I got to meet some of them on my journey. It was quite rewarding to have had a role in shaping people’s decisions about their lives and careers and exposing them to pathways that they’re incredibly passionate about. That wider impact always made me much prouder than any product deliverables or any direct work outcomes. Despite that pride, I still couldn’t shake the feeling that I was effecting change from behind a desk. My intuition told me that I wanted a deeper level of intimacy with and empathy for people who don’t have access to some of the learning opportunities that I’ve been lucky enough to enjoy.</p>

<h3 id="talk-to-experienced-people">Talk to experienced people</h3>

<p>Another lasting and impactful influence was a conversation I had with my cousin Obi during my time in Palo Alto. Obi Okobi was a product of the Harvard Graduate School of Education who went on to become a principal in Baltimore, Maryland’s school systems so I figured she was the perfect person to talk to about my job and interests in education. She was seated next to me at a celebratory dinner last year for my brother’s graduation from Stanford and we ended up having a very stimulating conversation about creativity’s role in education.</p>

<p>Sadly, that was the last conversation I’d ever have with my dear cousin. Shortly afterward, tragedy struck and Obi succumbed to a medical emergency at the all-too-early age of forty. In this loss were powerful lessons:</p>

<ul>
  <li>It isn’t rational to indefinitely defer our urges to investigate feelings that resonate with our true selves. We never know when the day may come that we run out of chances to do so. <strong>When something meaningful calls to us, we should at worst, find a way to explore that energy with mitigated risk, or at best, pursue that calling with vigor.</strong></li>
  <li>Obi’s life was a life of service and that was very much reflected in the way people chose to remember her. I’d like to be remembered in a similar fashion—as somebody who dedicated themself to service and lead by example in that regard (as Obi has been a leader for me).</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<img alt="Obi Okobi" src="/assets/img/2017-12-01-obi.webp" />
<figcaption>Obi having a good time at a wedding</figcaption>
</figure>

<blockquote class="bigquote">
<em>It is high time the ideal of success should be replaced with the ideal of service… Only a life lived for others is a life worthwhile.</em>
<br /><br />
<cite>—Albert Einstein</cite>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="on-finding-paving-a-way">On finding (paving) a way</h2>

<p>Making service a priority is easier said than done. Like any other worthwhile thing in life, committing to a mission and figuring out a way to make it work may require no small amount of sacrifice. Learning to part with things you hold dear in order to evolve is one of the hardest things to learn while growing up—but in retrospect, learning lessons the hard way has always worked fairly well for me. At certain times, there is no greater motivator than the prospect of failure. However, nearly all the time, there is no greater teacher than the acceptance thereof.</p>

<h3 id="do-whats-necessary">Do what’s necessary</h3>

<p>In order to ambitiously commit, take risks, help others, and understand my purpose, I had to identify failures in my life, accept them, and make difficult decisions about how to deal with them in order to move past them.</p>

<ul>
  <li>I chose to undergo therapy to ensure that I could take care of my own mental and emotional health as I transitioned into adulthood. I learned that much of life concerns reacting to events in a way that prioritizes growth.</li>
  <li>I chose to start accepting more responsibility and to hold myself accountable whenever I could identify a personal failure. I learned that even when entirely legitimate, blame is a formidable obstacle to progress.</li>
  <li>I chose to get off the bench, put up more shots, and keep taking some risks. I learned that establishing a framework for managing risk and exercising it with discipline can be rewarding in cases of both failure and success.</li>
  <li>I chose to part with a toxic family environment that was feeding my negativity, stifling my growth, and systematically removing my self-belief. I learned that hard decisions may be momentarily painful but that I can and will survive through them to ultimately find greener pastures.</li>
  <li>I chose to relinquish most of my material possessions; I packed what I could carry on my back and left home. I learned to greatly expand the radius of my comfort zone by strongly distinguishing wants from needs and assets from liabilities when life got tough. I learned to appreciate my merits and worth as a human aside from perceived wealth and status.</li>
  <li>I chose to set moments aside where I could consciously appreciate the things I was grateful for. I learned that fortitude and optimism are habits cultivated through consistent practice.</li>
  <li>I chose to continue helping others whenever possible despite a drastic reduction in material resources. I learned that contributing to the lives of others can lend us more positive energy to fight our own battles as well.</li>
  <li>I chose to recognize when I truly need help and to ask for it. I learned that I don’t have to be a martyr in order to serve others or to lead by example to propagate the change I’d like to see; sometimes we all need support.</li>
</ul>

<p>When people solicit advice for how to improve their lives, they often default to an additive frame—<em>what more can I do to reach my goals?</em> Something often overlooked is that a subtractive approach can be equally or more beneficial—<em>what should I <strong>stop</strong> doing to reach my goals?</em> Once I simplified my life by removing conflicting variables and starting over with a bottom-up approach, it became a lot harder to lie to myself. I could see far more lucidly after the fog of cognitive dissonance had dissipated. I was still a bit lost, but in the words of some corny motivational poster, <strong><em>it feels good to be lost in the right direction.</em></strong></p>

<h3 id="do-what-feels-right">Do what feels right</h3>

<p>I suspect that by nature I’m largely a defensive pessimist: a person who protects themself and others by identifying reasons <em>not</em> to take some action. Unbalanced defensive pessimism is not a suitable disposition for someone who wishes to squeeze the most out of this life by taking intelligent risks, growing through failures, and earning the rewards of successes. I had to shed my propensity for deliberating in place of acting if I ever wanted to see beyond the horizons that were confining me to passive mediocrity.</p>

<p>One good thing about service is that it is righteous. Despite all of the logistical difficulties that committing to a mission of service entails, choosing whether or not to help people who are truly in need is one of the easiest moral and philosophical decisions I could ever place in front of myself. Combining that with my newfound independence and my resolution to radically accept responsibility was a surefire cure for debilitating pessimism. The facts were that I truly wanted to do something which I felt was entirely possible and that I had neither a moral nor philosophical reason not to; <strong>any other reason not to was merely an excuse not to commit.</strong> The only way I could rationalize those excuses now was to accept responsibility. <em>The only reason not to commit to something this righteous is a lack of willingness to slog through the difficulties along the way. The only reason not to follow through with this is because of a contentment with passive mediocrity.</em></p>

<h3 id="do-it">Do it.</h3>

<p>I followed through.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="on-pursuing-commitment">On pursuing commitment</h2>

<p>Commitment is frightening. Committing to something truly worthwhile involves sacrifice, but moreover it demands steadfastness. Human beings are nomadic and dynamic creatures that crave change and novelty; remaining constant and stable in the face of shifting moods, environments, and circumstances is no easy task for us. Following through on commitments requires a tolerance for poor weather—the resolve to rise and power through the days when things get difficult or when the engine of raw passion doesn’t provide the thrust we so often rely on it for.</p>

<p>I found that when I learned to cope with the fact that my life circumstances got tougher, committing to long-term goals got much easier. I was no longer the kind of person who had to wait around until things were perfect to make decisions or take a big leap of faith. I knew now that I could start off in the right direction and adjust my course along the way. I recognized the benefits of maintaining an optimistic attitude and building upon positive momentum.</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">I decided to commit half a year to volunteering in Thailand.</blockquote>

<p>I’m working at the <a href="https://www.fr-ray.org/">Father Ray Foundation</a> in Pattaya, an organization that provides a home and access to education to over 850 disadvantaged children and young people with disabilities. My role within the organization includes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>teaching three English courses for vocational students with disabilities and special needs students</li>
  <li>designing and developing curricula and assistive technology for blind students to learn vocational and conceptual technology skills</li>
  <li>playing with and emotionally supporting children throughout the organization’s several projects</li>
  <li>leading various recreational activities for the youth</li>
  <li>assisting with the organization’s fundraising efforts</li>
</ul>

<figure>
<style>.embed-container { position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden; max-width: 100%; } .embed-container iframe, .embed-container object, .embed-container embed { position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; }</style><div class="embed-container">    <iframe title="YouTube video player" width="640" height="390" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/lZL3wTFm1rU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<figcaption>A short documentary about the Father Ray Foundation's work and mission (February 2017)</figcaption>
</figure>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>Commitment also forces one to reckon with the opportunity costs of investing deeply in something and promising to follow through. However, something I learned about paving my own path in life is that with a lot of determination and a little creativity, we can make difficult situations work to our advantage. In becoming a more flexible person, I came to understand that I really didn’t have to give up many of the things that truly appealed to me (especially things concerning my future). I could also choose to look at what opportunities long-term commitment <em>afforded</em>.</p>

<p><strong>I thought volunteering for six months would cost me the opportunity to land a steady job in my industry</strong> with a reasonable paycheck that could help me start my life as an independent adult. However, it afforded me a structure in which I could learn new skills, try many things, and deeply contemplate what things I enjoy working on most before making my next commitment. I am currently writing, designing, and doing more things that I’m passionate about than I have in a long time. I’m sure that my next move will be one that I am equally excited about instead of one which I settle for and I see everything as a positive step towards that outcome.</p>

<p><strong>I thought that moving to a different country would cost me the opportunity to fix things with my family.</strong> In reality, it afforded me distance to realize that everybody needs time to heal and that the nature of our relationships changes throughout our lifetimes as we grow and adjust with those around us. Navigating a different culture and teaching young people have taught me lessons in patience that extend to other areas of my life. It doesn’t come naturally, but I am finally permitting myself to be patient with my own growth; the peace of mind that brings to my life is quite invaluable.</p>

<p><strong>Lastly, I thought that committing to a mission of service far away from home would cost me the opportunity to spend time around my friends and the people I love.</strong> What I instead realized is that there is love to be found anywhere one goes and that it lifts us up, carries us through difficult times, and gives us the strength to surmount the challenges that shape us into the people that we wish to be. That reciprocity and appreciation make serving others an unparalleled privilege.</p>

<p><strong>To commit to and act on our love for others is to love ourselves.</strong> I’ll end with a warm quote from the whiteboard in the hallway this morning:</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote"><em>The heart of a volunteer is never measured in size, but by the depth of the commitment to make a difference in the lives of others.</em>
<br /><br />
<cite>—DeAnn Hollis</cite>
</blockquote>

<div class="soft-break mt-50"></div>

<p>Thank you very much for taking the time to read about something that matters a lot to me. 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+My+Motives+for+Service.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> if you’d like to connect about causes, work, and values that are important to you.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday</name></author><category term="community" /><category term="reflection" /><category term="design" /><category term="work" /><category term="travel" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How and why I committed to living and volunteering half a world away from my comfort zone]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Q&amp;amp;A: Why are toxic, competitive attitudes so common in the design community?</title><link href="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Q&amp;amp;A: Why are toxic, competitive attitudes so common in the design community?" /><published>2017-11-22T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2017-11-22T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://stedmanhalliday.com/blog/2017/11/22/toxic-design-community"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-massimo.webp" alt="Massimo Vignelli" /></p>

<p class="mt-200"><em>Q&amp;A is a column in which I'll post long-form answers to thought-provoking questions. This particular question and its answer are reposted from thread in <a href="https://www.facebook.com/groups/340004709510141">Designers Guild</a>, a Facebook community that I moderate. Designers Guild consists of 10,000+ designers committed to discussing, learning, and growing together.</em></p>

<h2 class="mt-200">The question</h2>

<p><em>A number of discussions last week revolved around design’s prevailing cultural prioritization of competition over cooperation (the collaborative ethos we often see in software development and engineering circles, especially in open-source communities).</em></p>

<p>Some quotes for context:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>There’s a heavy tendency for designers to compete and contrast themselves with one another rather than cooperate…</em></p>

  <p><em>I guess what I’m not understanding is why designers are less primed to being good at working together in an open-source context than engineers…</em></p>

  <p><em>I’ve also seen design folks click [sic] out into camps, and compete with each other when there was no reason to… (yikes, why do we do that, it’s like we need the pat on the back or the recognition…)</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>It would seem that toxic, competitive attitudes which impede collaboration are a widely recognizable problem in the design industry. But the question is: <em>where does the mindset behind the toxicity come from?</em></p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h2 id="the-answer">The answer</h2>

<p>One easy answer that addresses the cultural difference between design and software engineering in this regard is rooted in software’s historical context.</p>

<h3 id="a-brief-history-of-collaboration-in-software-development">A brief history of collaboration in software development</h3>

<p><strong>Software has grown into the monolith it is today with transparency, openness, and community hardwired into its DNA.</strong></p>

<p>Because software development originated in academic research environments, the principles of cooperation and openness for the sake of collective intellectual advancement were easy carryovers from the scientific and academic communities. It also helped that software was not the massively commoditized industry that it has since become; originally there was little incentive to stray from this model.</p>

<p>Richard Stallman effectively spearheaded the free software movement when he announced the GNU Project. In 1985, he founded the <a href="https://fsf.org">Free Software Foundation</a> and penned the <a href="https://www.gnu.org/gnu/manifesto.html">GNU Manifesto</a>, enumerating his reasons for believing so strongly in the values that free software promulgates. Some standout excerpts:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>I consider that the Golden Rule requires that if I like a program I must share it with other people who like it. Software sellers want to divide the users and conquer them, making each user agree not to share with others. I refuse to break solidarity with other users in this way. I cannot in good conscience sign a nondisclosure agreement or a software license agreement…</em></p>

  <p><em>So that I can continue to use computers without dishonor, I have decided to put together a sufficient body of free software so that I will be able to get along without any software that is not free…</em></p>

  <p><em>Everyone will be permitted to modify and redistribute GNU, but no distributor will be allowed to restrict its further redistribution. That is to say, proprietary modifications will not be allowed. I want to make sure that all versions of GNU remain free…</em></p>

  <p><em>Once GNU is written, everyone will be able to obtain good system software free, just like air…</em></p>

  <p><em>Copying all or parts of a program is as natural to a programmer as breathing, and as productive. It ought to be as free.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Richard Stallman, <em>GNU Manifesto</em></cite></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bigquote">In a word, what Stallman values so staunchly (in addition to freedom) can be described as <em>fellowship.</em></blockquote>

<p>Linus Torvalds followed in Stallman’s footsteps with the open release of the Linux kernel’s source in the early 1990s (later relicensed under a GNU General Public License: a free software license authored by Stallman himself). The combination of GNU’s free software and operating system with the Linux kernel brought about the first entirely free software environment for users. Neither that achievement, nor the entirety of the modern-day Linux ecosystem (not to mention countless other technologies) would be possible without the spirit of fellowship that united thousands of volunteer developers with the aim of constructive collaboration.</p>

<p>The idea of fellowship propagated even further throughout the development community with the advent of the World Wide Web. Tim Berners-Lee proposed and executed his early vision of the Web at CERN, another research environment where open informational exchange was a value of paramount importance. Furthermore, the Web was created for exactly that purpose: it enabled researchers to exchange and browse information with far more efficiency… and exchange they did!</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Tim Berners-Lee" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-berners-lee.webp" />
    <figcaption>Tim Berners-Lee at CERN in 1994 next to an early iteration of the World Wide Web.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Collaboration and the willing exchange of information continue to be absolutely crucial to the world of software development today. It’s not difficult to see how these ethics are structurally enforced by some undeniable industry realities, specifically:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The idea that “everything is built on something that was built on something that was built in 1970” encourages borrowing code as a productive and necessary practice.</li>
  <li>Carefully reading documentation (authored by some other developer) and searching for sources of previously shared information (e.g. Google-fu and browsing Stack Overflow) are some of the most essential platform-independent skills for any professional developer out there today.</li>
</ul>

<p>So far, this historical background does an alright job of explaining how collaboration has been valuable to software development in the past, but we still lack a satisfactory answer to our main question.</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">I believe that the essential differences in each industry's culture surrounding willing collaboration come down to categorical differences in how creative value is construed.</blockquote>

<h3 id="why-is-fellowship-valuable-to-engineers">Why is fellowship valuable to engineers?</h3>

<p>As a discipline, engineering is outcome-oriented and largely favors vertical progression. Achievement usually means rigorously honing a focused skillset and digging deeper to spawn new technical outcomes within a specific scope or domain. As an analogy, consider two miners, each in search of a different mineral—let’s say iron and lead. The iron miner has no real interest in unearthing lead other than to trade it with the lead miner for the iron ore that they recover, and the lead miner has a similar attitude. They’ve staked different claims and stated different goals, so they’re not truly competing with one another. However, each stands to gain immensely from collaborating with the other.</p>

<p>By trading ore with one another and sharing mining secrets and techniques, the miners can increase both of their yields. It doesn’t even matter if the result is that the iron miner extracts more lead ore: they would’ve used the same amount of mining resources in their search for iron anyway, but now they can earn revenue by trading with their neighbor. Similarly for the lead miner, all the lead ore that they are trading with the iron miner to obtain would’ve been inaccessible to them anyway, seeing as the iron miner has already staked their claim on that land. This is now ore in the hand that can be traded for at face value rather than prospected for with expected losses.</p>

<p>In a similar fashion, developers don’t really see themselves as direct competitors with others who happen to be digging a different hole (they may often view each other as indirect competitors in the abstract, which leads to rampant impostor syndrome and software development’s own brand of toxic and condescending attitudes, but that’s another story).</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Coal miners" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-miners.webp" />
    <figcaption>"Real miners don't use Pascal." 🙄</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Additional value can also be created on massive scales when insights arise from the intersection of a developer’s own vertical progress with their understanding of parallel innovations. This is similar to the <a href="https://priceonomics.com/the-correlation-between-arts-and-crafts-and-a/">correlation between artistic hobbies and scientific achievement</a>. To summarize, Nobel-Prize-winning scientists are 280% as likely to have a hobby in the arts as are scientists in general. The underlying theory is that experience and vertical achievement in the sciences can cross-pollinate with avocational creative exploration to lend new insights to the scientist’s practical career endeavors.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Nobel scientist hobbies" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-nobel-hobbies.webp" />
    <figcaption>A University of Michigan study found that elite scientists have a particular affinity for artistic hobbies.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>A good example of value created by crossover innovation in software is how neural networks (a highly academic subject confined to the relatively inaccessible fields of machine learning and deep learning research only a few years ago) are now a fairly commonplace component of consumer technology products. This couldn’t have happened without parallel research in the fields that artificial intelligence is applied to, such as imaging (computer vision and image recognition) and language and acoustics (speech recognition and natural language processing). A neat example that demonstrates both of these ideas is the application of deep learning to <a href="https://blogs.nvidia.com/blog/2016/05/25/deep-learning-paints-videos/">visual art processing</a> and <a href="https://shafeentejani.github.io/2016-12-27/style-transfer/">style transfer</a> (the abilities of AI to identify the styles of a images and apply them to other images).</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="Deep Photo Style Transfer" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-style-transfer.webp" />
    <figcaption>Researchers from Cornell University and Adobe take an original photo (left) and a reference image (center) as input and combine them output a new image (right). This technique is called <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/1703.07511">Deep Photo Style Transfer</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It turns out that accepting help and being helpful in return are… well, helpful! In the famed words of Sir Isaac Newton (from a letter to Robert Hooke about collaboration, of all subjects):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>If I have seen further it is by standing on ye sholders [sic] of Giants.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Sir Isaac Newton, letter to Robert Hooke</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote class="bigquote">It doesn't discredit developers to borrow the techniques that they use to achieve their goals because it is the rigor behind executing outcomes that is valued and celebrated.</blockquote>

<p>That’s not to say that the creativity and ingenuity involved in execution are not praiseworthy (in fact, they are frequently lauded). It’s just that the first and most important question in software development is whether or not the outcome actually works.</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">Ultimately, being a developer is all about having the grit to corral everything together into a practical outcome.</blockquote>

<h3 id="why-do-designers-systematically-fail-to-value-fellowship">Why do designers systematically fail to value fellowship?</h3>

<p>In contrast to software engineering’s cultural endorsement of vertical progression, creative disciplines (design included) largely incentivize horizontal progression. This is an inevitable consequence of rewarding the originality of outcomes and intellect over the rigor of process. For a long time, being a big-name designer hasn’t been about developing reliable and repeatable processes to consistently meet industrial goals. Instead, the idea of success in the design world has largely revolved around the ability to effectively wield cultural capital and trade on style, voice, and personality.</p>

<p>To return to the mining metaphor, imagine if the miners from before had redefined their success along the terms of who has claimed the best stake (not to be confused with the stake that has the highest mineral yield… just the “best” stake, whatever that may arbitrarily mean). The game then becomes all about seeking out new ground, staking a claim, and defining your hole according to criteria that position it as superior to all others dug before it. Within this value system and with these judgment criteria, every miner actually is in direct competition with the next. The design analogs:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Seeking out new ground</strong>—generating and executing on an “original” concept or aesthetic</li>
  <li><strong>Staking a claim</strong>—accepting credit for the intellectual labor involved in the generating novelty and/or success of a project</li>
  <li><strong>Touting your hole as superior</strong>—cleverly rationalizing your design decisions; criticizing others’ design decisions in equal or greater measure; utilizing past successes, cultural knowledge, voice, and cultural identity to increase your brand profile as a designer</li>
</ul>

<blockquote class="bigquote">In other words, an inordinate amount of the work concerns talking about the work in order to convince others of the the value of the design solution and, by extension, the designer's originality and intellect.</blockquote>

<p>I’ll let Mike M. tell it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><em>Everyone who ever told you good work sells itself was a lying jerk… I was told that good work, really good work, sold itself. And that if you had to stoop to selling it you were demeaning the profession. This is shit advice from shit people.</em></p>

  <p><cite>—Mike Monteiro</cite></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Monteiro makes a <a href="https://medium.com/mule-design/everyone-who-ever-told-you-good-work-sells-itself-was-a-lying-jerk-65acc1a72f74">good case</a> for why it’s a necessity for designers to develop ancillary presentation skills and learn how to speak about their work. But if it’s true that really good work can’t even sell itself, surely there must be a problem, no? <strong>The implication here is that clients cannot readily understand the value of design without some kind of presentation.</strong></p>

<p>Why is the value of design so inapparent? I’d posit that it’s because most designers don’t explicitly understand how exactly design adds value to its substrates in accordance with their own values and thinking patterns. They may have an intuition for the fact that design has a net-positive effect when executed appropriately, but the fact that the cult of design so frequently values the wrong things (perceived aesthetic novelty and conceptual intellect) makes the value of design incredibly difficult for even designers to quantify.</p>

<p><strong>It would behoove many a designer to realize that value in the realm of commerce is a business concept and not a philosophical one.</strong> Convincing other people of design’s value is about quantifying what it can do for their businesses. Watch <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RKXZ7t_RiOE">this video</a> posted in a Designers Guild discussion this week where Chris Do gives a phenomenal master class in just some of the ways that designers can discuss value when doing business. (Note: it’s very different from the ways in which most designers represent the value they can provide to businesses and that’s why it’s successful.)</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>The current difficulty with surmounting the design industry’s impasse of misplaced philosophical values arises from the fact that most of 20th century design ran on <strong>auteur theory</strong> (the idea that a single creator is responsible for executing all aspects of a collaborative creative work). Auteur theory is what emphasizes stylistic originality and the intellect of the individual creator above all other important factors that bring a creative project to fruition.</p>

<p>Auteur theory is why we have design “legends” and “rockstars.” It’s why <a href="https://eyeondesign.aiga.org/the-11-types-of-trendy-graphic-design-paul-rand-hated/">Paul Rand</a>, <a href="http://designobserver.com/article.php?id=15458">Massimo Vignelli</a>, and many other a graphic design granddad have wielded cultural capital amassed over their entire careers to convincingly decry nearly everything that’s succeeded them in the postmodern era. Although their criticisms are not entirely invalid, one might question the motives behind such vigorous disapproval of alternative approaches to craft.</p>

<p>How else could these legends of old defend their status as auteurs other than with vigorous criticism? They’re supposed to be singular geniuses who are irreplaceable provisioners of value. In practice, that all too often translates to devaluing things that deviate from modernism (the one <em>successful</em> and <em>correct</em> way to add value—if clients don’t believe that, modernists don’t get paid; if the culture doesn’t believe that, modernists don’t get legacy clout). This is the fault of auteur theory at its peak, and its vestiges are largely to blame for the commonplace toxicity and non-collaborative values in design today.</p>

<figure>
    <img alt="David Chathas collage" src="/assets/img/2017-11-22-david-chathas-collage.webp" />
    <figcaption>It's 2017, y'all still mad?! (Images courtesy of <a href="http://www.bestgraphicdesignerintheworld.com/">David Chathas</a></figcaption>
</figure>

<p>Another problem with rewarding formal originality and perceived intellectual inventiveness over all else is that it makes it difficult to trace the genealogy of ideas, which tell us a lot about how to create value in the future. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=oww7oB9rjgw">“Steal like an artist,”</a> has quite a different ring to it than Newton’s modest musings on the shoulders of giants. It’s not too often that software strictly requires anyone to provide citations either, but because the field has developed a culture that does not penalize collective achievement and the re-synthesis of existing ideas, the majority of developers share their resources quite enthusiastically.</p>

<p>In contrast, the value system in the present design landscape ensures that in most cases, we still systematically fail to attribute value to team members whose work goes unrecognized. Additionally, appreciating the output of the designers whose work an outcome intellectually builds upon is optional at best… but things seem to be getting better.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<h3 id="a-better-future-for-the-value-of-design">A Better Future for the Value of Design</h3>

<p>One good thing about the intersections of design, technology, business, and analytics is that creatives are being held to a more universal and honest standard that is quantifiable from a business perspective. It’s good to be original to the extent that one can, but what do novel outcomes beget in the real world; in other peoples’ utilitarian value systems?</p>

<blockquote class="bigquote">When we cease to reward design outcomes solely for perceived originality and individual intellect, and instead begin to hold them to standards defined by results, maybe the world will better understand the value of design.</blockquote>

<p><em>How suitable was this strategy for the target market? How did this campaign create growth?</em> <strong>If design is a practice of aesthetic utility, designers should probably ask utilitarian questions and take utilitarian measurements.</strong> The leaders who ushered in the precursors of modern design at the Bauhaus a century ago may have made strides into adopting a more scientific process for creating work… but as far as feedback for assessing work, we’re mostly still thinking like artists.</p>

<p>Perhaps if designers start measuring their outcomes in addition to critiquing them, everyone’s contributions to process can come forth and find value. <strong>When people feel valued for their contributions, they contribute abundantly instead of viewing intellect as a scarce resource to sequester for their own gain.</strong> When designers manage to value one another and incentivize valuable contribution on an industry-wide scale, the benefits of collaboration and fellowship will have become central community tenets.</p>

<div class="soft-break"></div>

<p>What did you think of this post? 
<a href="https://x.com/messages/compose?recipient_id=1632742023991300096&amp;text=Hey%2C+I+just+read+Q%26A%3A+Why+are+toxic%2C+competitive+attitudes+so+common+in+the+design+community%3F.">Message me on X (Twitter)</a> and let me know if you’ve got thoughts on any of these topics.</p>]]></content><author><name>Stedman Halliday for [Prototypr](https://blog.prototypr.io/)</name></author><category term="design" /><category term="engineering" /><category term="software" /><category term="community" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Structural and historical rationales for fellowship and competition in design practice]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="https://stedmanhalliday.com/assets/og-image.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>